<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<document>

  <properties>
    <title>Studio Manual - Chapter 2</title>
    <author email="dev@avalon.apache.org">Avalon Documentation Team</author>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="Chapter 2 - Concepts">
      <!-- 2.1 -->
      <subsection name="Merlin" >
        <p>
          The Merlin project is committed to ....
        </p>
        <!-- 2.1.1 -->
        <subsection name="Component">
          <p>
            A component is a logical unit of one or more classes and related
            artifacts which together implement a functionality. A component 
            delivers his functionality only through its "component interface”. 
            There can be one or more "component interface implementations”.
          </p>
          <p>
            A component is not aware of its functional environment - eg. a 
            component can be deployed predictably in different application 
            scenarios and environments. 
          </p>
          <p>
            A component is always responsible for the correctness of the 
            incoming data / objects.
          </p>
          <p>
            A component is described by a "component type descriptor” (Type) 
            which holds immutable information associated with the component 
            implementation and its interface (Metadata). Based on information 
            accessible from an instance of Type a container has available the 
            structural and runtime dependencies that an instance of a 
            corresponding component will require. 
          </p>
          <p>
            In Merlin metadata are stored either in XML or in a binary format.
            Metadata are created automatically by "Magic” - which is the build
            tool for Merlin - or by Eclipse Studio from JavaDoc tags contained
            in the components interface or implementation.
          </p>
          <p>
            Components in Merlin can get their information either through a 
            freely configurable and extendable set of interfaces or by 
            constructor injection. 
          </p>
          <p>
            The following set of interfaces are delivered as standard by Merlin:
          </p>
          <dl>
            <dd>Lifestyle Management</dd>
            <dt>
              Merlin provides support for different component instantiation 
              policies. These policies are referred to as lifestyles. Examples
              of lifestyle include 'singleton', 'per-thread', 'pooled' and 
              'transient'.
            </dt>
            <dd>Lifecycle Management</dd>
            <dt>
              Merlin provides support for constructor based injection of 
              lifecycle artifacts, or optional phased delivery under which a 
              component is processed through a series of lifecycle stages. 
              Lifecycle processing involves the execution of a series of stages
              such as associating a logging channel, applying a configuration or
              component parameters, setting the runtime context, supplying 
              dependent services, initialization, startup, shutdown and 
              disposal. Within the Merlin system, lifecycle stages can be 
              extended or modified through association of other components 
              that provide lifecycle support. Merlin distinguishes these 
              services as deployment dependencies as distinct from classic 
              runtime dependencies.
            </dt>
          </dl>
        </subsection>
        <!-- 2.1.2 -->
        <subsection name="Block / Services" >
          <!-- 2.1.2.1 -->
          <subsection name="Block" >
            <p>
              In Merlin a block is a logical and physical unit of one or more 
              components and its related artifacts. One artifact is the blocks
              metadata which contains information like its containing 
              components, classloader directives and the "services” it delivers.
            </p>
            <p>
              Other artifacts of a block might be persistence mapping 
              information for contained components etc.
            </p>
            <p>
              Physically a block is deployed in a standard jar file. To make it
              possible to identify blocks visually Merlin blocks are using the 
              ".bar” file extension.
            </p>
            <p>
              It's quite usual that the term "block” and the term "component" 
              are used equivalent. 
            </p>
          </subsection>
          <!-- 2.1.2.2 -->
          <subsection name="Service" >
            <p>
              A block can declare the export of a set of services established by
              the components contained within it. This enables a container to 
              function as a composite component relative to its peers. This 
              composition is either done by "nested” or by "referenced” blocks.
            </p>
          </subsection>
          <!-- 2.1.2.3 -->
          <subsection name="Nested Blocks" >
            <p>
              An "include” directive in a block instructs Merlin to include an 
              external block within the container. Services exported by the 
              block will be made available to other components at the same 
              level as the included block
            </p>
            <p>
              With the "include” directive a block is included "by value” into a
              block. This is especially useful  to structure larger blocks into 
              smaller reusable blocks. 
            </p>
          </subsection>
          <!-- 2.1.2.4 -->
          <subsection name="Referenced Blocks" >
            <p>
              A "container” directive is used to reference other blocks / 
              containers. Only services declared in the referenced block are 
              accessible by the parent block. This directive is used to assemble
              a whole application by reusable blocks.            
            </p>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <!-- 2.1.3 -->
        <subsection name="Kernel / Container" >
          <p>
            In Merlin every block is covered by its own container. The "startup”
            program, which instantiates and manages all the subsequent 
            containers is called the "kernel”. 
          </p>
          <p>
            Through that architecture Merlin assures a very secure and 
            encapsulated runtime environment for each block. 
          </p>
        </subsection>
        <!-- 2.1.4 -->
        <subsection name="Facilities / Application blocks" >
          <p>
            Merlin differentiates two types of blocks: On one hand "application 
            blocks” and on the other hand "Facilities”.
          </p>
          <!-- 2.1.4.1 -->
          <subsection name="Facilities" >
            <p>
              Facilities are just normal blocks with the exception of:  
            </p>
            <ul>
              <li>
                Facilities are able to access the kernel and its container
                model.
              </li>
              <li>
                Facilities are used to extend the functionality of the core 
                Merlin container in a plugable and flexible manner. 
              </li>
              <li>
                Facilities include technical services like JMX, messaging,
                logging, persistence, workflow etc.
              </li>
            </ul>
            <p>
              This separation of concerns enables the enhancement or even 
              exchange of kernel implementations without touching the 
              implementation of the application blocks. This is one of the key
              features of Merlin which ensures on one hand a large stability 
              for application blocks against technology change and on the other
              hand a high flexibility to adopt new technologies and to enhance
              the core functionality of Merlin.             
            </p>
          </subsection>
          <!-- 2.1.4.2 -->
          <subsection name="Application Blocks" >
            <p>
              Application blocks may also be hierarchically composed. But 
              because this is not naturally darstellbar it is limited to one 
              block.
            </p>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
        <!-- 2.1.5 -->
        <subsection name="Server" >
        </subsection>
        <!-- 2.1.6 -->
        <subsection name="Repository" >
        </subsection>
      </subsection>
      <!-- 2.2 -->
      <subsection name="Eclipse" >
        <!-- 2.2.1 -->
        <subsection name="Preferences" >
        </subsection>
        <!-- 2.2.2 -->
        <subsection name="Properties" >
        </subsection>
        <!-- 2.2.3 -->
        <subsection name="Builders" >
        </subsection>
        <!-- 2.2.4 -->
        <subsection name="Help" >
        </subsection>
        <!-- 2.2.5 -->
        <subsection name="Component Configurator" >
        </subsection>
      </subsection>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
