<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE document SYSTEM "dtd/document-v10.dtd">

<document>
  <header>
    <title>Overview</title>
    <authors>
      <person id="FB" name="Federico Barbieri" email="fede@apache.org"/>
      <person id="BL" name="Berin Loritsch" email="bloritsch@apache.org"/>
      <person id="LS" name="Leo Simons" email="mail@leosimons.com"/>
      <person id="PD" name="Peter Donald" email="donaldp@apache.org"/>
    </authors>
  </header>
  <body>
    <s1 title="What is it?">
      <p>
       The Avalon project is an effort to create, design, develop and maintain
       a common framework and set of components for applications written 
       using the Java language. This framework is not a standalone product, 
       but allows existing and yet to be created applications to fit 
       into a common platform and to share code, design and human resources.
      </p>
    </s1>
    <s1 title="Project Goals">
      <p>
        As many people point out, software engineering is a very uncommon procedure
        in software development and even more uncommon in auto-organized open
        source projects. The main goal of this project is to design a way for
        different projects to share resources avoiding as much as possible efforts
        duplication. 
      </p>
      <p>
        The Avalon Team are proud to announce a new whitepaper that covers how
	to develop with Avalon. It covers the Framework, and touches on the
	LogKit and Excalibur. You can find
	<link href="./developing/index.html">Developing with Apache Avalon</link>
	on this site.
      </p>
    </s1>
	<s1 title="Sub-Projects">
	  <p>
	    There are several distinct sub-projects that together form the Avalon project:
	  </p>

      <s2 title="LogKit">
		<p>
          <link href="@LOGKIT_BASE@/index.html">LogKit</link> is the logging toolkit 
          used by the Avalon subprojects.
        </p> 
      </s2>
      
      <s2 title="Framework">
        <p>
          <link href="framework/index.html">Framework</link> provides a specification of 
          design patterns and rules in the form of interfaces. Also provided are default 
          implementations of those interfaces.
        </p>
        <p>
          The framework is not a product or an API set or a set of interfaces: it is
          a collection of code design patterns, rules, guidelines and suggestions on how to
          write software that "plugs" into the framework. The framework does not
          impose restrictions on the application that uses it, but rather precious guidelines to
          help the developers reuse as much work they can from other solutions. 
        </p>
      </s2>

      <s2 title="Excalibur">
		<p>
          <link href="excalibur/index.html">Excalibur</link> is a collection of often-needed 
          reusable components. It includes tools for threading, pooling, datasources, 
          proxies and more.
        </p>
      </s2>

      <s2 title="Phoenix">
		<p>
          <link href="@PHOENIX_BASE@/index.html">Phoenix</link> is a server orientated
          Application Server. Applications and Services that conform to the framework
          rules can be hosted in Phoenix. The Application server manages the applications
          classloader, security and logging needs. It also provides a JMX-based management 
          facility.
        </p>
      </s2>

      <s2 title="Cornerstone">
		<p>
          <link href="@CORNERSTONE_BASE@/index.html">Cornerstone</link> is a repository.
          for what we call <link href="@PHOENIX_BASE@/what-is-a-block.html">blocks</link>,
          which provide services vital to server applications. The blocks include blocks for
          services such as scheduling and socket management. It also has some demo applications 
          that demonstrate the proper use of Phoenix and can be used as a starting point for 
          your own servers.
        </p>
      </s2>

      <s2 title="Testlet">
        <p>
          The <link href="@TESTLET_BASE@/index.html">Testlet</link> subproject is a unit 
          testing framework used by the other sub-projects.
        </p>
      </s2>

	</s1>
  </body>
  <footer>
    <legal>
      Copyright (c) @year@ The Jakarta Apache Project All rights reserved.
      $Revision: 1.1 $ $Date: 2001/07/18 14:35:40 $
    </legal>
  </footer>
</document>
