<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document> 
  <properties>
    <author email="dev@avalon.apache.org">Avalon Documentation Team</author>
    <title>Contributors</title>
  </properties>
  <body> 
    <section name="Stephen Mcconnell">
      <p>(mcconnell at apache dot org)</p>
      <img src="/images/people/mcconnell.jpg"/>
      <h3>Background</h3>
      <p>
      Long experience in the area of open-source software.  Member of the management
      team for the Apache Directory Project (LDAP), initiator and founding Member of 
      the Apache Avalon PMC (components and containers), Lead architect of the Merlin 
      component management platform. Expert in component based development, service 
      oriented architecture, and reuse strategies leveraging component composition.
      </p>
      <p>
      Chaired the Object Management Group Electronic Commerce Domain Task Force 
      from 1996 through to 1999, during which time I facilitated the 
      establishment of a common reference architecture and technology adoption process 
      covering B2B community collaboration standards (receiving an OMG 
      Distinguished Service Award in 2000).  Over the last six years, I've been 
      responsible for the coordination of a number of collaborative research and 
      development activities related to the delivery of a distributed service 
      management platform (OSM, France) and the <i>osm.planet</i> global service management 
      architecture.
      </p>
      <p>
      International experience in business development 
      across the United States, Europe and Japan. I've been responsible for ground 
      breaking technology developments within the Australian, North American and 
      European IT industry.  I've successfully managed the delivery of commercial 
      products in the Computer Aided Design industry, high-end proprietary simulation 
      applications in the pharmaceuticals industry (Pilkington Glass, US), production 
      systems in the ceramics industry (Caroma, Aust), and world-class innovations in 
      simulation related to underground and open-cut mining industries (Newmont Mining, 
      Aust).  I've also led several international projects dealing with distributed 
      service management in the B2B and financial services domain (OSM, France).  
      </p>
      <h3>Recent Positions</h3>
      <table>
        <tr>
          <th>Dates</th>
          <th>Year</th>
          <th>Country</th>
          <th>Organization</th>
          <th>Position</th>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>2003</td>
          <td></td>
          <td></td>
          <td>DPML</td>
          <td>Founder</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>1997-2004</td>
          <td>7</td>
          <td>France</td>
          <td>OSM</td>
          <td>Chief Technology Officer</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>1992-1996</td>
          <td>6</td>
          <td>France</td>
          <td>ARTTIC</td>
          <td>Senior Consultant</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>1984-1991</td>
          <td>8</td>
          <td>Australia</td>
          <td>Finite Development</td>
          <td>Executive Officer</td>
        </tr>
      </table>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>

