<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>

<!-- 
 Copyright 2004 Apache Software Foundation
 Licensed  under the  Apache License,  Version 2.0  (the "License");
 you may not use  this file  except in  compliance with the License.
 You may obtain a copy of the License at 
 
   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 
 Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
 distributed  under the  License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
 WITHOUT  WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS  OF ANY KIND, either  express  or
 implied.
 
 See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
 limitations under the License.
-->

<document>

  <properties>
    <title>Planet - Facilities</title>
    <author email="dev@avalon.apache.org">Avalon Development Team</author>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="Using the Reflector Facility">
      <p>
        The Reflector has two pre-defined blocks that can be used straight
        up without any further configuration.
      </p>
      <p>
        Example of including the Complete block in a larger block;
      </p>
<source>
<![CDATA[
<container name="myapplication" >
  <classloader>
    :
  </classloader>
  
  <component name="MyComponent" type="com.mycompany.myproject.MyComponent" />
  
  <include 
    artifact="block:metro/facilities/reflector/metro-reflector-blocks-complete#SNAPSHOT" />
  
</container>
]]>
</source>
      <table>
        <tr>
          <th>Group</th>
          <th>Name</th>
          <th>Purpose</th>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>metro/facilities/reflector</td>
          <td>metro-reflector-blocks-complete</td>
          <td>
            The Complete block consist of everything need when you don't have
            the HTTP Facility available and used elsewhere in the system. It
            starts the HTTP Facility on port 8080 with a normal socket listener
            and registers the composition model as a root object in the 
            Reflector.
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>metro/facilities/reflector</td>
          <td>metro-reflector-blocks-standard</td>
          <td>
            The Standard block is intended for use when you want it to attach
            itself to an existing HTTP Facility running on any port. By default,
            the Reflector will lookup 'any' <code>HttpContext</code>, so it is
            not defined which context it will add itself to. If you need better
            control, you need to use the 'manual assembly' features of Merlin.
          </td>
        </tr>
      </table>
      <subsection name="Normal Use - My own Root objects." >
        <p>
          If you want to have your own root objects, you look up the Reflector
          and call the <code>addRootObject( String name, Object object )</code>
          method, either directly from your component, or preferably from a 
          separate component that does the registration.
        </p>
<source>
/**
 * @avalon.dependency type="org.apache.metro.facilities.reflector.ReflectorService"
 *                    key="reflector"
 * @avalon.dependency type="com.mycompany.myproject.MyApplication"
 *                    key="app"
 */
public void service( ServiceManager man )
    throws ServiceException
{
    MyApplication app = (MyApplication) man.lookup( "app" );
    ReflectorService reflector = (ReflectorService) man.lookup( "reflector" );
    reflector.addRootObject( app );
}
</source>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Normal Use - Direct utlization of Reflector" >
        <p>
          There are sometimes reasons to use the Reflector programmatically
          and not using it as a troubleshooting tool only. For instance,
          let's say that you define the entire application with events, and
          that you want to enable that the user can subscribe to changes 
          via mail. You can then utilize the Reflector to provide for a 
          fairly understandable object model, i.e. the dot-notation, and
          have a mail application register itself at each of the objects
          defined in the mail. Another example of use is a report generator,
          which has its fields defined with the dot-notation of the objects
          that are the live data in the form.
        </p>
        <p>
          The <code>ReflectorService</code> interface is fairly easy to 
          understand and has many convenience methods to make these sorts
          of applications easier to write.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Advance Use - Defining my own TypeHandler" >
        <p>
          There might be reason to handle the containment of certain types
          differently than the standard <code>ObjectTypeHandler</code>. Reasons
          for this varies, but typically it would be that there are additional
          information in the class or interface that you want to view or change.
          You create a <code>TypeHandler</code> and implement each of the 
          methods.
        </p>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <th>Method signature</th>
            <th>Description</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
    boolean isDefault();
            </td>
            <td>
              All implementations should return false, unless the purpose is
              to provide a new default behaviour, instead of the 
              <code>ObjectTypeHandler</code>. This method is only called once
              upon startup.
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
    String[] getNames( Object container )<br/>
    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;throws ReflectionException;
            </td>
            <td>
              This method should return an array of all the members of the
              class. This determines which members are available in the type
              the TypeHandler handles. This method is called for every object
              introspected by the Reflector. The names returned will be used
              as input in the methods below (i.e. the membername argument).
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
    Class getClass( Object container, String membername )<br/>
    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;throws ReflectionException;
            </td>
            <td>
             Return the Class of the member. The Class returned must be the
             type of the reference, and not the Class of the object assigned to
             the reference. In case of JavaBeans get methods, the Class returned
             equals the return type of the get method. If the Class of the
             object assigned to the reference is returned, then assignment
             of new objects to the same reference will be required to be the
             same class or a subclass of the Class returned from this method.
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
    Object&#160;getMemberObject(<br/>&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Object&#160;container,&#160;String membername )<br/>
    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;throws ReflectionException;
            </td>
            <td>
              Return the object with the given membername.
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
    void&#160;setMemberObject( &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Object&#160;container,&#160;String&#160;membername,&#160;Object&#160;value&#160;)<br/>
    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;throws ReflectionException;
            </td>
            <td>
              Assignment of a new value to a member. For primitive types and
              the subclasses of Number, the value (or true/false in case of
              boolean) can either be the numeric object, or a string with
              the value in it. For Number types a Double object will be
              created and assigned. For all other types, you can pass a
              String with the fully qualified class name, and a new object
              of that class will be instantiated and assigned, provided that
              the class can be found through the classloader hierarchy and
              that it has a default (i.e. empty) constructor.
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
    boolean&#160;isSettable(&#160;Object container,&#160;String memberName&#160;)<br/>
    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;throws ReflectionException;
            </td>
            <td>
              This method should return <code>true</code> if it is possible
              to modify the member, i.e. call the <code>setMemberObject</code>
              method.
            </td>
          </tr>
        </table>
      </subsection>
    </section>
  </body>

  <footer>
    <legal>
      Copyright (c) @year@ The Avalon Apache Project All rights reserved.
      $Revision: 1.4 $ $Date: 2004/05/05 13:38:05 $
    </legal>
  </footer>
</document>
