<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by J Aaron Farr (Sony Electronics) -->
<document>
	<properties>
		<author email="dev@avalon.apache.org">Avalon Documentation Team</author>
		<title>History</title>
	</properties>
	<body>
		<section name="Avalon's Story">
			<p>
        The following is an attempt at recording the history of
	Avalon, both its technology and its community.  The Avalon Framework
	traditionally had a notorious learning curve and the community
	has seen a number of changes.  Hopefully by understanding
	where Avalon has been, users can gain a better understanding of
	where Avalon is now and where we are headed.
      </p>
		</section>
		<section name="Once upon a time">
			<p>
Let's start off with some basic history. Avalon emerged from the Java
Apache Server Framework before the days of Apache Jakarta. During
development of the JServ project (which laid the foundation for
Tomcat), many of the developers realized that the ideas being used at
the time could be abstracted into a general application
framework. This framework eventually became the Avalon framework we
have today.  The framework focused a small number of core concepts 
(design patterns) called Separation of Concerns and Inversion of
      Control which are described elsewhere.
     </p>
			<p>
So in the beginning there was the Avalon Framework. It basically
described the contracts or interfaces between various components (such
as lifecycle methods) and provided some general utilities for using
these interfaces. One could easily create an application which simply
just used the framework. However, in order to provide some more
advanced components and utilties (which were not essential to the
framework, but still useful) Excalibur was born.
    </p>
			<p>
Excalibur held a set of basic components and utilities which made
working with the Framework much easier. One of these components was
the Excalibur Component Manager or ECM which did all the work of
getting all your component and configuration data sorted out and
started. It was the first container of sorts and grew out of work from
the Cocoon project. ECM didn't have a lot of "advanced" features, but
it was simple to work with and could be used in any number of
environments. 
    </p>
			<p>
Of course, with time, new expectations and requested features meant
that other Avalon containers were under development.  ECM would have to
share the spotlight with Phoenix. 
   </p>
		</section>
		<section name="The Rise of the Phoenix">
			<p>
Phoenix was the first really complete full fledged standalone
container for Avalon. Phoenix was not only a container, but a
microkernel. While it could be used for other sorts of applications,
most Phoenix development revolved around server applications such as
web servers, FTP servers, telnet servers, etc. Phoenix applications
would take a number of components and bundle them together in what was
called a block.  A block generally referred to a complete application,
such as a database or FTP server, although you could have inter-block
dependencies. Blocks would be packaged up with configuration and
assembly files into a .sar archive, similar to the .ear files for J2EE
applications. Phoenix would then launch all the SAR blocks contained
within a particular startup directory. 
    </p>
			<p>
Thus Phoenix was a full application server of sorts. Applications
running within Phoenix used the Avalon Framework just as ECM
components would. In fact, if you were careful to only depend on the
framework for development, with a little work you could get
applications written for ECM to run in Phoenix and visa versa. 
   </p>
			<p>
Cornerstone became a repository of Phoenix blocks: larger components
which could be dropped into Avalon Phoenix and provide services and
resources to user developed components and applications. There was
some overlap between components developed in Cornerstone and
Excalibur, but in general, Cornerstone components were targeted for
server side applications running in Phoenix. 
   </p>
			<p>
Phoenix's growth brought changes to the developer community as well.
A separate CVS repository and specific mailing list were
created to facility the Phoenix community.  This was the beginning
of a sort of schism within Avalon, both technologically and socially,
as the new containers created with them their own communities,
standards, and goals.  There was a a tug of war, so to speak, between
keeping the different containers compatible while also allowing each 
developer community to explore and enhance their software in their own
repective ways.  One of those enhancements was the change from
components to services.
   </p>
		</section>
		<section name="How Components Became Services">
			<p>
In the beginning there were only components. The components had a role
defined by a java interface and an implementation defined by a
concrete java class. In ECM roles and components could be described in
a set of XML configuration files, generally one for the roles and one
for the implementations. In Phoenix, roles were still roles and
components were still components, but they were defined in xinfo files
scattered across the various jar archives that would make up an
application. This was done to allow developers to deploy a jar file
that contained not only the interfaces and implementations, but also
the basic meta-data. The xinfo files and the conf files had the
same purpose (to hold meta-data and meta-info) but were used by 
different containers.  Thus, from the beginning there was no common
meta format or API.
     </p>
			<p>
Also at this time, all components were children of the one
org.apache.framework.component.Component interface. A brave developer
scaled Mt. Doom and tossed the Component interface and all the other
marker interfaces into the fiery pit, thus freeing all components from
bondage of the one Component. 
    </p>
			<p>
Upon return from this quest, the developer said, "All Components shall
now be dubbed Services" and a new set of Service Managers and Service
Selectors appeared that could converse with any Object, not just
Components. These Service utilities performed the exact same functions
as their deprecated Component counterparts, but didn't require
everything be a Component. That is:
    </p>
			<source>
      Component componentManager.lookup(String role); 
    </source>
			<p>
became
   </p>
			<source>
      Object serviceManager.lookup(String role); 
   </source>
			<p>
So in this sense, Components ARE Services. But now the Avalon
community had two names for the same thing and this is generally were
confusion arises.  Since that time, a service generally refers to only
the service interface while a component refers to the entire interface
and implementation together.
   </p>
			<p>
Stephen McConnell, primary developer of Merlin, chimed in with this
clarification: "A 'component' is an implementation artifact that
exposes 0..n services. A 'service' is computation contract exposed by
a component. A component may include many other features that are not
exposed through the services that is publishes. "
   </p>
			<p>
"A 'service' is typically represented by a Java interface and possibly
supporting meta-info (such as a version, attributes, etc.)." 
   </p>
			<p>
"A 'component' is an example of a 'service-delivery-strategy'."
   </p>
		</section>
		<section name="Fortress and Merlin arrive">
			<p>
Effort was made in Phoenix to support the new Service semantics, but
instead of rewritting ECM, the decision was made to create a new
ECM-like container which could use Components and Services alike. Thus
was born Fortress.
  </p>
			<p>
Fortress supports legacy ECM components but provides a number of
features like basic meta-data configuration (instead of a "roles"
file), dynamic service activation, lifecycle extensions,
instrumentation support and so on. Fortress is also "embeddable" in
that you can easily start up a Fortress container in your own
application be it a Java Swing client or a Servlet. Fortress provides
no default standalone client (i.e.- there's no "main" method class in
Fortress) and doesn't do much classloader magic, making embedding a
little more predictable. Fortress was released in the summer of 2003
and replaced ECM as Avalon's light weight container of choice. 
  </p>
			<p>
While Fortress grew from ECM, Merlin grew from Phoenix, though it
quickly developed beyond its roots. Merlin focused on a strict
seperation between container concerns and component concerns. As such,
all Merlin applications are never dependent on any actual Merlin code
(at least in order to compile). A new meta data model was developed,
hierarchical block support added, and Merlin provided support for
standalone or embedded environments. 
  </p>
			<p>
For the sake of completeness, we should also mention Tweety which was
a very basic container developed for the sole purpose as a teaching
tool.  Tweety never really made it out of the sandbox much, but it
is not forgotten by some ...
  </p>
		</section>
		<section name="One container to rule them all">
			<p>
If you're keeping up with our story you'll have realized by now that
we have four containers: ECM, Phoenix, Fortress, Merlin.  At its
height, Avalon also contained its own logging framework (LogKit), unit
testing framework, two component libraries (Excalibur and
Cornerstone), and a host of Avalon-based server applications including
a web server and FTP server.  It was a lot to handle.
   </p>
			<p>
Moreover, while all of these software projects and components were
based on the same Avalon framework, they were often mutually
incompatible.  The framework was intentionally designed to be
rather silent on the issues of meta-info and meta-data (information
about how to wire components together inside a container) amongst
other things.  This meant that each container implementation had its
own "standards" and made writing container neutral components rather
difficult.
   </p>
			<p>
When Avalon moved out of Apache Jakarta in late 2002 and on to its own
top level project, the developers decided to try to organize the
situation; however, they faced a bit of an identity crisis:  What was
Avalon about?  Containers?  Frameworks?  Components?  All of the
above?  Was Avalon to be an umbrella project with many containers
based on a single framework or a single project with a single
reference implementation?
   </p>
			<p>
To make a long story short, the pendulum swung back and forth on that
issue for the better part of two years.  Several projects where spun
off or depricated and some developers left to persue other adventures.
In the spring of 2004 there was another push to consolidate Avalon's
software projects into a single platform:
   </p>
			<source>
     One container to rule them all
     One container to find them
     One container to bring them all
     And in the model bind them
   </source>
			<p>
After a few months of proposals and counter proposals, Avalon emerged
as a project focused on a single container platform: Merlin.  The
Fortress and Excalibur codebases were then transferred to the new <a href="http://excalibur.apache.org">Apache Excalibur</a> project.
Meanwhile, Phoenix was retired in light of its fork, <a href="http://loom.codehaus.org">Loom</a>, which was developed at
Codehaus by some early Avalon developers.
  </p>
		</section>
		<section name="Peering into the Mysts of Avalon">
			<p>
At its inception, Avalon was a rather novel software project and
pioneered many ideas in container development.  Since that time, the
concepts of Separation of Concerns and Inversion of Control have
become buzzwords and a whole slew of IoC frameworks and containers
have emerged.  Avalon continues to push the bounds of these
technologies and remains focused on developing a complete solution for
component and container applications.  The Avalon team invites you to
download our software and join our community mailing lists and become
involved in Avalon's future.
    </p>
		</section>
	</body>
</document>
