<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section>
  <title>Create a new block</title>

  <para>In MerlinStudio a block is equivalent to an eclipse project. Therefor
  we will use the term "block" in this document as a synonym to "project".
  </para>

  <para>In order to create a block you have to create an eclipse project with
  a special project nature. This is done by the following steps:</para>

  <para>1. Select the menu item File &gt; New &gt; Project.... or press the
  "new project" button in the toolbar to open the New Project wizard</para>

  <para><inlinegraphic fileref="../../../resources/NewProject.gif" /></para>

  <para>Select the "Merlin development" category and than "create a block".
  Note that the "show all wizards" checkbox has to be checked!</para>

  <para>Press "Next". </para>

  <para><inlinegraphic
  fileref="../../../resources/NewProjectPage.gif" /></para>

  <para>2. In the new project wizard enter the project name. This is done
  exactly the same way as you do it with normal Java projects</para>

  <para><inlinegraphic
  fileref="../../../resources/NewProjectSelection.gif" /></para>

  <para>3. In the next wizard page you can select the type of block you would
  like to start with.</para>

  <para>With the current version of MerlinStudio there are only a few types of
  example blocks available. This will be changed in future versions so that
  one has a full range of ready to use blocks / components. </para>

  <para>Note: All example blocks are created by an highly flexible template
  engine which is integrated within MerlinStudio. This template engine enables
  you to create and deliver your own standard blocks. How to use the template
  enginge will be elaborated later in this manual.</para>

  <para>4. After you have selected a block template and press "Finish" the
  complete eclipse project - aligned with your selected block type - will be
  created for you. You should now see a new eclipse project with a similar
  structure:</para>

  <para><inlinegraphic fileref="../../../resources/PackageView.gif" /></para>

  <para>Congratulations! You have just created your first Merlin block /
  component.</para>
</section>