<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <author email="dev@avalon.apache.org">Avalon Documentation Team</author>
    <title>Avalon Central</title>
  </properties> 

  <body>
    <section name="Xdoc Task">
      <p>
      The xdoc task provides support for document generation. 
      </p>
      <p>
        The XDoc task takes a <em>Theme</em> that is installed in 
        the project system directory, $(project.system}/themes, and invokes two
        XSLT stylesheets to the documents in the document source directory. 
        There are properties to define which theme to be usedand which the 
        output format to generate. The theme must support the given output 
        format.
      </p>
      <p>
        The generation occurs in 2 steps. First the navigation.xml files are
        aggregated. In effect, this means that only the local context of 
        the navigation is required in each directory. This is done by using
        the <em>nav-aggregate.xsl</em> stylesheet in the theme.
        In the second step, the content is transformed, using the 
        <em>transform.xsl</em> stylesheet in the theme. See separate
        documentation for information on how to write a theme.
      </p>
<source><![CDATA[
<x:xdoc/>
]]></source>

      <p><i>Example of the xdoc task output when updating this site:</i></p>

<pre>xdoc:
   [x:xdoc] Filtered source: F:\dev\avalon\central\site\target\build\xdocs
    [mkdir] Created dir: F:\dev\avalon\central\site\target\temp\xdocs
   [x:xdoc] Destination: F:\dev\avalon\central\site\target\docs
    [mkdir] Created dir: F:\dev\avalon\central\site\target\docs
   [x:xdoc] Year: 2004
   [x:xdoc] Theme: F:\dev\avalon\central\system\themes\modern\html
   [x:xdoc] Transforming navigation.
     [copy] Copying 413 files to F:\dev\avalon\central\site\target\temp\xdocs
   [x:xdoc] Transforming content.
     [copy] Copying 2 files to F:\dev\avalon\central\site\target\docs
     [copy] Copying 60 files to F:\dev\avalon\central\site\target\docs</pre>

      <subsection name="Properties">
        <table>
          <tr><th>Property</th><th>Default</th><th>Description</th></tr>
          <tr>
            <td>${project.organization.name}</td>
            <td>The Apache Software Foundation</td>
            <td>
              The name of the organization. Used to create the copyright notice
              at the bottom of the page.
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>${project.target.temp.xdocs}</td>
            <td>xdocs</td>
            <td>
              The directory where the documents will be copied prior to its
              transformation. This is to enable use of filtering. The 
              directory is relative to the general output directory.
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>${project.xdocs.src}</td>
            <td>xdocs</td>
            <td>
              The directory where the source documents reside. This directory
              is relative to the general source directory.
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>${project.xdocs.resources}</td>
            <td>resources</td>
            <td>
              Resources needed, such as images and raw HTML files are placed in 
              this directory. The directory is relative to the general source
              directory.
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>${project.xdoc.theme}</td>
            <td>modern</td>
            <td>
              The name of the theme. Themes have to be installed in the project
              system directory, ${project.system}/themes, and the theme name
              must exist as a directory there-under.
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>${project.xdoc.output.format}</td>
            <td>html</td>
            <td>
              The output format of the generated content. The theme must be
              constructed to support the given output format. <em>modern</em>
              currently only supports the <em>html</em> format.
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>${project.xdoc.logo.left.file}</td>
            <td></td>
            <td>
              The logo to be displayed at the top left corner on every page.
              The theme may or may not use this.
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>${project.xdoc.logo.left.url}</td>
            <td></td>
            <td>
              The URL that the top left logo will be linked to.
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>${project.xdoc.logo.middle.file}</td>
            <td></td>
            <td>
              The logo to be displayed in the middle at the top on every page.
              The theme may or may not use this.
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>${project.xdoc.logo.middle.url}</td>
            <td></td>
            <td>
              The URL that the top middle logo will be linked to.
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>${project.xdoc.logo.right.file}</td>
            <td></td>
            <td>
              The logo to be displayed at the top right corner on every page.
              The theme may or may not use this.
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>${project.xdoc.logo.right.url}</td>
            <td></td>
            <td>
              The URL that the top right logo will be linked to.
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>${project.xdoc.brand.name}</td>
            <td>Avalon</td>
            <td>
              The Brand Name is used by the <em>modern</em> theme as the small
              heading at the top of every page. Below the Brand is the page 
              title, found in the XML file.
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>${project.xdoc.anchor.url}</td>
            <td></td>
            <td>
              This is the root URL of where the public sources of the documents
              can be found. This will be used for the XML icon in 
              <em>modern</em> to link the html page to its current source 
              document.
            </td>
          </tr>
        </table>
      </subsection>    
    </section>
  </body>
</document>

