<?xml version="1.0"?>

<changes title="Avalon Phoenix - History of Changes">
 <header>
  <title>Changes</title>
 </header>
    <devs>
    <author name="Federico Barbieri" email="fede@apache.org" id="FB"/>
    <author name="Berin Loritsch" email="bloritsch@apache.org" id="BL"/>
    <author name="Peter Donald" email="peter@apache.org" id="PD"/>
    <author name="Paul Hammant" email="Paul_Hammant@yahoo.com" id="PH"/>
    <author name="Mircea Toma" email="mirceatoma@home.com" id="MT"/>
  </devs>
<release version="4.0a3" date="November 13, 2001">
  <action dev="PD" type="change">
    Add documentation describing BlockListener.
  </action>
  <action dev="PD" type="change">
    Fixed bug that allowed binary distributions to be built without
    copying xerces.jar into correct place.
  </action>
</release>
<release version="4.0a2" date="November 12, 2001">
  <action dev="PD" type="change">
    Update Phoenix to use the new Avalon Framework Logger interface rather than
    directly using LogKits Logger class. This required a backwards incompatible
    change in BlockContext. The getLogger() methods now return the Logger interface
    rather than LogKits Logger class. If a Block implements Loggable then it will
    be passed LogKits Logger, this is required for backwards compatability. If the
    Block implements LogEnabled it will receive the new style Logger.
  </action>
  <action dev="MT" type="add">
    Add support for undeploying and unistalling applications. Add support for separating
    out install phase from deployment phase and persisting information about
    application installations.
  </action>
  <action dev="PD" type="change">
    Rework the application deployment format (ie .sar format) to be more in line
    with other specifications. See docs/creating-a-server-application.html in distribution
    for current format description. The old format is deprecated but will still work.
  </action>
  <action dev="PH" type="add">
    Created the start of a Phoenix Developers Kit (PDK) that will enable
    developers to rapidly become accustom to developing Phoenix applications.
  </action>
  <action dev="PD" type="add">
    Started to incorporate the JMX code more fully into Phoenix kernel. Started
    doing this by refactoring the base MBeans and testing using the RIs agent.
  </action>
  <action dev="PD" type="change">
    Separated code that validated assembly of application into separate
    classes. The validation is now much stricter and requires that
    Blocks conform to established patterns. The validation phase should give
    more reasonable explanations for violations. Extra validation checks
    include verifying that services offered by a Block are actually interfaces,
    that there is no circular dependencies, that declared Blocks and BlockListeners
    actually implement Block or BlockListener interface, that the names of Blocks
    are valid etc.
  </action>
</release>
<release version="4.0a1" date="September 25, 2001">
  <action dev="BL" type="change">
    Too many things to enumerate here.  This is the first public release,
    and the code is still considered alpha.  In future releases, we will
    be much more careful to record the changes to Phoenix.
  </action>
</release>
<release version="3.1a2" date="Unreleased">
    <action dev="BL" type="add">
      Added stylesheet to convert Stylebook markup to DocBook markup.
    </action>
    <action dev="BL" type="change">
      Changed the documentation build process to use Cocoon to build
      the site.
    </action>
  <action dev="PD" type="remove">
    Legacy support for nested configuration elements in assembly file
    removed.
  </action>
  <action dev="PD" type="update">
    Simplified Loader and made it set ContextClassLoader before executing
    Main method. It will also use the System property phoenix.home if set
    rather than always trying to dynamically determine home directory.
  </action>
  <action dev="PD" type="add">
    Added SingleAppEmbeddor to launch a kernel to load a single Application.
    Patch supplied by "Eung-ju Park" (colus@isoft.co.kr). This is useful if
    you need to reuse the blocks in other contexts (such as in a Servlet).
  </action>
  <action dev="PD" type="add">
    Made default SystemManager a NoopSystemManager. Patch supplied
    by "Eung-ju Park" (colus@isoft.co.kr). To re-enable RMI manager a new
    command line switch "--remote-manager" was added.
  </action>
  <action dev="PD" type="update">
    Reworked SecurityManager setup. Instead of starting a security
    Manager inside the code it has been re-architectured so that the
    SecurityManager is set on the command line. This was to avoid a number
    of issues related to creating a URLClassLoader in an unprotected context
    before setting SecurityManager. ie As AccessControllerContext was null it
    is impossible to use ClassLoader.getResource(AsStream)(). This means that
    defining phoenix.insecure will no longer disable the SecurityManager. The
    replacement method is to set the native OS environment variable
    'PHOENIX_SECURE=false'.
  </action>
  <action dev="PD" type="update">
    Separate Parsing of CLI arguements into separate class (CLISetup).
    This is to facilitate launching Phoenix as a native daemon using
    Tomcats Services API.
  </action>
  <action dev="PD" type="add">
    Started Localizing text strings throughout Phoenix. This is done using
    ResourceManager and Resources from Avalon/Excalibur project.
  </action>
</release>

</changes>
