<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE changes SYSTEM "dtd/changes-v10.dtd">

<changes title="Avalon/Phoenix History of Changes">
  <devs>
    <person name="Federico Barbieri" email="fede@apache.org" id="FB"/>
    <person name="Berin Loritsch" email="bloritsch@apache.org" id="BL"/>
    <person name="Peter Donald" email="donaldp@apache.org" id="PD"/>
  </devs>
<release version="4.0a1" date="September 25, 2001">
  <action dev="BL" type="change">
    Too many things to enumerate here.  This is the first public release,
    and the code is still considered alpha.  In future releases, we will
    be much more careful to record the changes to Phoenix.
  </action>
</release>
<release version="3.1a2" date="Unreleased">
    <action dev="BL" type="add">
      Added stylesheet to convert Stylebook markup to DocBook markup.
    </action>
    <action dev="BL" type="change">
      Changed the documentation build process to use Cocoon to build
      the site.
    </action>
  <action dev="PD" type="remove">
    Legacy support for nested configuration elements in assembly file
    removed.
  </action>
  <action dev="PD" type="update">
    Simplified Loader and made it set ContextClassLoader before executing 
    Main method. It will also use the System property phoenix.home if set
    rather than always trying to dynamically determine home directory.
  </action>
  <action dev="PD" type="add">
    Added SingleAppEmbeddor to launch a kernel to load a single Application. 
    Patch supplied by "Eung-ju Park" (colus@isoft.co.kr). This is useful if 
    you need to reuse the blocks in other contexts (such as in a Servlet).
  </action>
  <action dev="PD" type="add">
    Made default SystemManager a NoopSystemManager. Patch supplied 
    by "Eung-ju Park" (colus@isoft.co.kr). To re-enable RMI manager a new
    command line switch "--remote-manager" was added.
  </action>
  <action dev="PD" type="update">
    Reworked SecurityManager setup. Instead of starting a security 
    Manager inside the code it has been re-architectured so that the
    SecurityManager is set on the command line. This was to avoid a number
    of issues related to creating a URLClassLoader in an unprotected context
    before setting SecurityManager. ie As AccessControllerContext was null it 
    is impossible to use ClassLoader.getResource(AsStream)(). This means that 
    defining phoenix.insecure will no longer disable the SecurityManager. The 
    replacement method is to set the native OS environment variable 
    'PHOENIX_SECURE=false'. 
  </action>
  <action dev="PD" type="update">
    Separate Parsing of CLI arguements into separate class (CLISetup).
    This is to facilitate launching Phoenix as a native daemon using
    Tomcats Services API.
  </action>
  <action dev="PD" type="add">
    Started Localizing text strings throughout Phoenix. This is done using 
    ResourceManager and Resources from Avalon/Excalibur project.
  </action>
</release>

</changes>
