<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>
  <header>
    <title>Guide - for Block Developers</title>

      <author name="Berin Loritsch" email="bloritsch@apache.org"/>

    <abstract>
      The Block Developer's Guide (BDG) is written to bring an overview
	  of how to create and deploy a Block. The Block is the component that
      is hosted in the Phoenix micro-kernel.
    </abstract>
  </header>
  <body>
    <section name="Who Should Read This Book?">
    	<p>The BDG is written for developers who want to create
		  blocks for Phoenix. It is assumed that you are familiar with Java, XML, Avalon
          patterns and server side security issues. This book provides an overview of
          the underlying technology, Java classes and interfaces, component model, and
          behavior of server Blocks within Phoenix.</p>
		<p>While this book concentrates on server fundamentals, it should not
		  be construed as a &#8220;dummy's&#8220; book. Server side programming
		  is complex because of the performance and security issues you must
		  balance.</p>
		<p>You should be well versed in the Java language and have some
		  practical experience developing server solutions. If you need a stronger
		  background on server side programming, I suggest finding a good book on the
		  subject (any suggestions?).</p>
	 </section>
     <section name="Organization">
      <p>
       Here is how the information is presented. The first few chapters are
       foundational material, and describe the basic concepts you can use in your
       own blocks. The later chapters specify in detail the formal requirements of
       Block implementations.
      </p>
	 </section>
     <section name="Contents">
       <ol>
        <li><a href="guide-block-developers-what-is-a-block.html">What is a block?</a></li>
        <li><a href="guide-block-developers-what-is-a-block-listener.html">What is a block listener?</a></li>
        <li><a href="guide-block-developers-what-is-an-application-listener.html">What is an application listener?</a></li>
        <li><a href="guide-block-developers-creating-a-block.html">How do I create a block?</a></li>
        <li><a href="guide-block-developers-making-phoenix-compatible-comps.html">How do I make my components phoenix-compatible?</a></li>
        <li><a href="reference-blockinfo-specification.html">BlockInfo specification</a></li>
       </ol>
      </section>
  </body>
</document>
