<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE document SYSTEM "dtd/document-v10.dtd">

<document>
  <header>
    <title>Avalon Phoenix - Reference - Development Roles</title>
    <authors>
      <person name="Leo Simons" email="leosimons@apache.org"/>
    </authors>
  </header>
  <body>
    <s1 title="Introduction">
      <p>
        In phoenix-based development, we identify several roles. Each of these has its own
	guide. If you plan to aid in the development of phoenix itself, or if you are
	responsible for all these aspects, you should read all the guides. Otherwise, you
	should be able to learn everything you need to know from the guide that fits your
	role.
      </p>
    </s1>
    <s1 title="The Administrator">
      <p>The administrator is responsible for getting phoenix to run and for keeping it
      running. He typically controls the startup and shutdown of the standalone server
      or daemon, and uses a management console to keep the server in top condition.</p>

      <p><link href="guide-administrator.html">Administrator's Guide</link></p>
    </s1>
    <s1 title="The Deployer">
      <p>The deployer manages (un/re)deployment of the applications hosted withing phoenix,
      typically through a management console. In real life, this is often the same person
       as the adminstrator.</p>

      <p><link href="guide-deployer.html">Deployer's Guide</link></p>
    </s1>
    <s1 title="The Assembler">
      <p>The assembler takes pre-written blocks and glues these together to create a
       server application. Assemblers usually work closely with block developers.</p>

      <p><link href="guide-assemblers.html">Assembler Guide</link></p>
    </s1>
    <s1 title="The Block Developer">
      <p>The block developer creates reusable components (called blocks) that can be
       wired together to form a server applications.</p>

      <p><link href="guide-block-developers.html">Block Developers Guide</link></p>
    </s1>
  </body>
  <footer>
    <legal>
      Copyright (c) @year@ The Jakarta Apache Project All rights reserved.
      $Revision: 1.1 $ $Date: 2002/05/12 19:52:50 $
    </legal>
  </footer>
</document>
