<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE document SYSTEM "dtd/document-v10.dtd">

<document>
  <header>
    <title>Avalon Phoenix - Overview</title>
    <authors>
      <person name="Berin Loritsch" email="bloritsch@apache.org"/>
      <person name="Peter Donald" email="peter@apache.org"/>
      <person name="Paul Hammant" email="Paul_Hammant@yahoo.com"/>
    </authors>
  </header>
  <body>
    <s1 title="Introduction">
      <p>
        Phoenix is a micro-kernel designed and implemented on top of the Avalon
        framework. It is both an API to program to and a reference implementation.
        The reference implementation provides a number of facilities to manage the
        environment of Server Applications. Such facilities include log management,
        classloading, thread management and security. In the future it will
        conditionally offer support extra facilities such as central server management,
        server pools, and other facilities aimed at reducing the time to market. The API
        defines a standard method of piecing togther server components and creating a server.
      </p>
    </s1>
    <s1 title="Documentation is coming">
      <p>
        Some of the information on this site is currently a bit out of date. We are
	working hard to fix this. If you come across any incosistencies or have a
	problem, please don't hesitate to contact us through the mailing list. Thank
	you.
      </p>
    </s1>
    <s1 title="Guide to Avalon Phoenix">
      <p>
        This guide starts with an architectural overview of Phoenix. Then, we identify
	the different roles that typically exist in daily use of phoenix. For each of
	these, we provide a basic guide. We finish with a complete example.
      </p>
        <s2 title="Target Audience">
          <p>
            This documentation is aimed towards people who:
            <ul>
	      <li>wish to create applications that run within phoenix</li>
	      <li>wish to create components (blocks) for use within phoenix</li>
	      <li>wish to setup and administer phoenix</li>
              <li>are interested in the design principles of Avalon Phoenix</li>
              <li>wish to develop code that will be incorporated into Avalon Phoenix</li>
              <li>wish to reuse Avalon Phoenix concepts in their own application</li>
            </ul>
          </p>
        </s2>
        <s2 title="Contents">
          <ol>
            <li><link href="guide-architecture.html">Architectural overview</link></li>
            <li><link href="guide-roles.html">Development roles</link></li>
            <li><link href="guide-administrators.html">Administrator Guide</link></li>
            <li><link href="guide-deployers.html">Application Deployer Guide</link></li>
            <li><link href="guide-assembler.html">Server Application Assembler Guide</link></li>
            <li><link href="guide-block-developers.html">Block Developer Guide</link></li>
            <li><link href="guide-example-configuration.html">Example Configuration.</link></li>
          </ol>
        </s2>
    </s1>
    <s1 title="Avalon Phoenix Reference Documentation">
      <p>
         Besides the
         <link href="api/index.html">Javadocs</link>, we have the
         <link href="guide-architecture.html">Architectural overview</link> to look at.
      </p>
    </s1>
  </body>
  <footer>
    <legal>
      Copyright (c) @year@ The Jakarta Apache Project All rights reserved.
      $Revision: 1.7 $ $Date: 2002/05/12 19:52:49 $
    </legal>
  </footer>
</document>
