<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE document SYSTEM "dtd/document-v10.dtd">

<document>

 <header>
  <title>Phoenix Todo</title>
  <authors>
   <person name="Avalon Documentation Team" email="avalon-dev@jakarta.apache.org"/>
  </authors>
 </header>

<body>

<s1 title="Todo">

<p>
This document describes functionality that is either missing or not finished 
within Phoenix.
</p>

<p>
Wish List functionality is stuff that we would like to see implemented, but is 
not critical for release. This is the area where you can take ownership of a 
part of the project and contribute back.
</p>

<p>
Very Important Work to Complete is stuff that we feel is holding up a release of 
Avalon.
</p>

<p>
If you are a new developer to Phoenix or even an existing developer, these are 
areas where you can take ownership and help complete. Please do not ask us how 
you can help, but rather specific questions about how you think that these items 
should be implemented. It is up to you to take initiative and provide solutions 
to the missing functionality described below. ;-) If your see yourself as more 
of a application (rather than infrastructure) writer, then perhaps peruse 
Cornerstone's to-do list - it's even more ambitious.
</p>

<p>
Documentation is *always* appreciated in any form. There are two ways to provide 
helpful documentation. The first way is to write up HTML or straight text 
documentation and send it to one of the primary authors directly (we are also 
willing to give you CVS write access if you wish). The second way is to post 
Questions/Answers to the FAQ under the Avalon sections there. 
There is a Getting Started document named 
"getting-started.html" that could always use additional documentation, examples 
and clarification. You need to take the initiative and just start writing down 
your thoughts and concerns and questions and answers and then giving those back 
to us.
</p>

<p>
If you need more detailed help, please join, then send mail to the mailing 
list (avalon-dev@jakarta.apache.org) and ask your specific questions there.
</p>

</s1>

<s1 title="Wish List">

    <s2 title="">
      <p>
      Refactor block validation code. Write an Ant taks that uses this 
      and validates the .bar files and another task that validates the
      assembly.xml file.
      </p>
    </s2>      
    <s2 title="Log messages">      
      <p>
      Refactor Log messages so that they are structured in a manner more 
      suitable for administrators rather than developers.
      </p>
      <p>
      Refactor Log messages so that they are structured in a manner more 
      suitable for administrators rather than developers.
      </p>
    </s2>

    <s2 title="Generated Configurations">
      <p>
      Define and implement a smart way to generate Avalon configurations.
      Define configuration template containing default configuration,
      user configuration file to overwrite or append configurations to template,
      implement code to merge all servers configuration file to a single Avalon
      configuration file.
      </p>
    </s2>

    <s2 title="Time Scheduler changes">
      <p>
      Rework the DefaultTimeScheduler so that entrys are removed from heap when
      reset. Otherwise it could lead to excessive buildup of invalidated entries 
      if many are reset but remain in heap.
      </p>
    </s2>

    <s2 title="Opening some tightly kernel-coupled services">
      <p>
      Rework kernel so that ConfigurationRepository, Logging and Management can
      be routed through ServerApplications.
      </p>
    </s2>

    <s2 title="Virtual File System / Jars within Jars">
      <p>
      Implement a simple read-only VFS so that .sar files do not need to be 
      expanded.
      </p>
    </s2>

    <s2 title="Thread pooling">
      <p>
      Rework kernel so that thread boundaries are respected and secure. This essentially
      involves using ThreadPools to execute phases and for management.
      </p>
    </s2>

    <s2 title="JNDI service">
      <p>
      Determine if we need a naming service. If so provide a simple JNDI based naming
      service possibly built on top of cadastre.
      </p>
    </s2>

    <s2 title="Block Management remotely">
      <p>
      Separate out and specify the way in which different parts of system are managed.
      ie Compare how remote Management of Blocks could occur vs Deployer/Kernel/Embeddor
      management occurs.
      </p>
    </s2>

    <s2 title="Hot deployment">
      <p>
      A standard system for hot deploying and undeploying. This may require the building
      of FileMonitors that will read a file when it is changed.
      </p>
    </s2>

    <s2 title="Reconfiguration">
      <p><strong>This has a few facets:</strong></p>
      <p>
      A standard reconfiguration system.  This may require the building
      of FileMonitors that will read a file when it is changed.  Any
      kind of block or component that extends the Reconfigurable interface
      gets sent the new configuration.
      </p>
      <p>
      A mechanism to allow one block to be the master of another's configuration 
      programmatically.  This would mean that whilst in use, the configuration
      could change.  It could happen invisibly or as part of human interaction 
      via some UI.  The blocks woyld be granted configuration-update rights in
      assembly.xml.  Discussed on the list in late Aug, early Sept 2001.
      </p>
      <p>
      Define and implement needed stuff to allow hot and warm reconfiguration at
      runtime.
      </p>
      
    </s2>

    <s2 title="Proxy Interfaces">
      <p>
      Rework kernel so that components are optionally provided via proxied
      interfaces. External services and management will also be provided via 
      proxy interfaces.
      </p>
      <p>
      (Update) DynamicProxy now exists in Excalibur, but it relies
      on a reflection way of proxying - there could be speed issues there.  It may 
      be better to replicate some features of Kawa's gnu.bytecode package to 
      genuinely make classes inside the VM.
      </p>
    </s2>

    <s2 title="Management Console">
      <p>
      Management console/Client interface. CLI version aswell as a GUI version.
      </p>
    </s2>

    <s2 title="Default JNDI Contexts">
      <p>
      Avalon should provide default JNDI contexts
      that Block implementers can extend and use like
      Context, EventContext, and DirectoryContext.
      </p>
    </s2>

    <s2 title="Java Messaging Service">
      <p>
      JMS (Java Messaging Service) for the Connection Manager. It
      will provide a standard and flexible connection service and
      messaging service. It allows for both point to point messaging
      and multicast messaging (subscriber/provider). 
      </p>
    </s2>

    <s2 title="Logging to database">
      <p>
      Support for sending log events to a database.  Not all logging
      systems will want to send information to the filesystem.
      </p>
    </s2>

    <s2 title="Multiple implementations of Persistence Store">
      <p>
      Persistent Store should be able to optionally store in a database.
      </p>
    </s2>

    <s2 title="Server Pools">
      <p>
      Support for server pools.  Several Phoenix servers should be able
      to pool resources and act as one server regardless of VM, or
      physical machine they are on.
      </p>
    </s2>

    <s2 title="Block loading remotely">
      <p>
      Remote loading of Blocks. Phoenix should be able to pull a block
      at run time from a remote server, check the signature, and run it
      with proper permissions.  This would allow for the possibility of
      automatically upgrading blocks.
      </p>
    </s2>

    <s2 title="Remote Control">
      <p>
      Write some code to remotely control Phoenix. (This will most likely be 
      rolled into JMX support).
      </p>
    </s2>

    <s2 title="Transactions">
      <p>
      Define and implement some Transaction pattern for the Repository. Maybe JTA?
      </p>
    </s2>
</s1>

<s1 title="Ongoing work">

    <s2 title="Documentation">
      <p>
      Write all documentation.
      </p>
    </s2>

    <s2 title="JavaDocs">
      <p>
      Update JavaDocs for decent developer documentation.
      </p>
    </s2>

</s1>

<s1 title="Very Important Work to Complete">

    <s2 title="Java Management eXtentions">
      <p>
      JMX (Java Management eXtentions) for central management of
      Avalon. If JMX cannot be done due to licensing, we should
      make the current beginnings of central management more
      robust.
      </p>
      <p>
      Leo Simmons, (our key JMX developer to Aug 2001) has gone off travelling, and 
      sadly will not be taking a laptop.  We're looking for people to work along 
      the lines of Apache princlples in a team to take over Leo's work and finish 
      this off.
      </p>
    </s2>

</s1>

</body>
</document>
