<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE document SYSTEM "dtd/document-v10.dtd">

<document>
  <header>
    <title>Overview</title>
    <authors>
      <person id="FB" name="Federico Barbieri" email="fede@apache.org"/>
      <person id="BL" name="Berin Loritsch" email="bloritsch@apache.org"/>
    </authors>
    <notice>
      Avalon documentation is under construction.  Everything you
      can find outside this page is to be considered obsolete.
    </notice>
  </header>
  <body>
    <s1 title="What is it?">
      <p>
       The Avalon project is an effort to create, design, develop and maintain
       a common framework and set of components for server applications written 
       using the Java language. This framework will not be a standalone product, 
       but will allow existing and yet to be created server applications to fit 
       into a common platform and to share code, design and human resources.
      </p>
    </s1>
    <s1 title="Project Goals">
      <p>
        As many people points out, software engineering is a very uncommon procedure
        in software development and even more uncommon in auto-organized open
        source projects. The main goal of the framework project is to design a way for
        different projects to share resources avoiding as much as possible efforts
        duplication. 
      </p>
      <p>
        The framework will not be a product or an API set or a set of interfaces: will be
        a collection of code design patterns, rules, guidelines and suggestions on how to
        write server software that "plugs" into the framework. The framework will not
        impose restrictions on the server that deploy it, but rather precious guidelines to
        help the developers reuse as much work they can from other server solutions. 
      </p>
    </s1>
<!--
    <s1 title="Features">
      <p>
      </p>
      <ul>
        <li>Prebuilt components combined with established design patterns will help 
        reduce your development cycle time and cost. This in turn decreases time to market.</li>
        <li>Avalon supplies the infrastructure, you focus on competitive differentiation
        in the market place.</li>
        <li>Being both Free Software and Opensource, Avalon is accessible to your developers
        and they can adapt it to suit your own needs. No more vendor lock-in or control.</li>
      </ul>
    </s1>
-->
  </body>
  <footer>
    <legal>
      Copyright (c) @year@ The Jakarta Apache Project All rights reserved.
      $Revision: 1.2 $ $Date: 2001/03/22 23:11:28 $
    </legal>
  </footer>
</document>
