<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.1//EN" "document-v11.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>Avalon Framework - Containers</title>
    <authors>
      <person id="PH" name="Paul Hammant" email="Paul_Hammant@yahoo.com"/>
      <person name="Leo Simons" email="leosimons@apache.org"/>
    </authors>
  </header>
  <body>
    <section>
<title>Introduction</title>
      <p>
        There are various containers that are aware of the Avalon Framework interfaces.
	This is a sort-of comprehensive list.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section>
<title>Standalone Containers</title>
      <p>
        These typically run from the command line and are launched via a legacy main() method.
      </p>
      <section>
<title>Avalon Phoenix</title>
        <p>
          This is a sister project to Avalon Framework.  It provides an environment
          for launching multiple, isolated, more or less unrestricted server applications
	  as hosted components.  These can be applications like a web server, RDBMS or
	  EJB server. It provides many advanced features like automatic management, at the
	  cost of a bit of complexity.
          See <link href="http://avalon.apache.org/phoenix/index.html">Phoenix</link>.
        </p>

	<p>
	  Phoenix is the oldest of the Avalon Containers; it is probably the most powerful
	  and most widely used. While still in alpha, this hints at the fact that we find it
	  to be not completely future complete, rather than an infantile project.
	</p>
      </section>

	<section>
<title>Avalon Excalibur's Tweety</title>
	<p>
	Tweety is almost the opposite of Phoenix. It is a recent development and written
	exclusively as a teaching tool. It has no features whatsoever besides basic support
	for the Avalon lifecycle. This results in a complete distribution the size of the
	Phoenix bootstrapper.
	See <link href="http://avalon.apache.org/excalibur/tweety">Tweety</link>
	</p>
	</section>

	<section>
<title>Myrmidon</title>
	<p>
	Myrmidon is a proposal for the kernel of
	<link href="http://jakarta.apache.org/ant">Apache Ant</link> 2.
	See <link href="http://cvs.apache.org/viewcvs.cgi/jakarta-ant/proposal/myrmidon/">Myrmidon</link>
	</p>
	</section>
    </section>
    <section>
<title>Embedded Containers</title>
      <p>
        These run inside another application (like a servlet engine) and are controlled by it.
      </p>
      <section>
<title>Excalibur Component Manager</title>
        <p>
          This is used by various applications like Cocoon. Cocoon is run inside the
          Sun specified servlet context of a web-app.  It is designed for such
          servlet-context reuse. ECM is the most stable of the containers (it is the
	  only one with a stable release); it is also arguably the worst design.
	  See <link href="http://avalon.apache.org/excalibur/component/">ECM</link>.
        </p>
      </section>
      <section>
<title>Fortress</title>
        <p>
          Fortress is meant as a future replacement of ECM. It fixes several of ECMs flaws
	  like a mixup of concerns. It is built to be very extensible, and it includes
	  support for custom lifecycle extensions. Fortress is still pre-alpha.
	  See <link href="http://avalon.apache.org/excalibur/fortress/">Fortress</link>.
        </p>
      </section>
      <section>
<title>Merlin</title>
        <p>
          Another recent development is Merlin, which has a client API very similar to
	  Phoenix (applications that can run within phoenix can run within merlin as
	  well). Merlin is still pre-alpha.
	</p>
	<p>
	  See <link href="http://home.osm.net/doc/merlin/index.html">Merlin</link>.
        </p>
      </section>
      <section>
<title>Plexus</title>
        <p>
          Plexus is a container under development that will become the basis of the
	  services framework for a sister project to Avalon,
	  <link href="http://jakarta.apache.org/turbine">Turbine</link>.
        </p>
	<p>
		See <link href="http://tambora.zenplex.org/cgi-bin/cvsweb.cgi/plexus/">Plexus</link>.
	</p>
	<note>
	Plexus is being developed outside of Avalon itself as an external project.
	</note>
      </section>
      <section>
<title>Enterprise Object Broker (EOB)</title>
        <p>
          The reference implementation of this EJB-replacement container runs on top of
          Phoenix.  EOB supports a subset of the Avalon Framework interfaces but allows
          RPC publishing of arbitary interfaces apparent in a hosted components object
          model.
        </p>
	<p>
		  See <link href="http://eob.sourceforge.net/">EOB</link>.
	</p>
	<note>
	EOB is an being developed outside of Avalon itself as an external project.
	</note>
      </section>
     </section>
  </body>
</document>
