<?xml version="1.0"?>
<status>

  <developers>
    <person name="Federico Barbieri" email="fede@apache.org" id="FB"/>
    <person name="Berin Loritsch" email="bloritsch@apache.org" id="BL"/>
    <person name="Peter Donald" email="peter@apache.org" id="PD"/>
    <person name="Paul Hammant" email="Paul_Hammant@yahoo.com" id="PH"/>
    <person name="Mircea Toma" email="mirceatoma@home.com" id="MT"/>
    <person name="Stephen McConnell" email="mcconnell@osm.net" id="SM"/>
    <person name="Nicola Ken Barozzi" email="nicolaken@apache.org" id="NKB"/>
  </developers>

  <todo>
    <actions priority="high">
      <action context="docs" dev="open">
        Improve docs.
      </action>
    </actions>
    <!-- Add todo items. @context is an arbitrary string. Eg:
    <actions priority="high">
      <action context="code" dev="SN">
      </action>
    </actions>
    <actions priority="medium">
      <action context="docs" dev="open">
      </action>
    </actions>
    -->
  </todo>

  <changes>
  
    <!-- Add new releases here -->
<release version="4.0a4" date="Unreleased">

    <!-- Sample action:
     <action dev="JB" type="fix" due-to="Joe Contributor"
             due-to-email="joec@apache.org">Fixed a bug in the Foo class.</action>
    -->

    <action dev="NKB" type="update">
       Move to Forrest http://xml.apache.org/forrest/ for document generation.
   </action>          
    <action dev="PD" type="add">
        Update documentation and move to Anakia for document generation.
   </action>
    <action dev="PD" type="add">
Remove deprecated functionality for deploying old style .sar files or
deploying from a directory.
   </action>
    <action dev="PD" type="add">
Remove deprecated Service interface.
   </action>
    <action dev="PD" type="add">
Remove some deprecated methods from BlockContext.
   </action>
     <action dev="PD" type="add">
Warn users if their blocks Work interfaces/Services implement
any lifecycle interfaces.
    </action>
    <action dev="SM" type="add">
       Allow name sub-element in block section of BlockInfo.
   </action>
     <action dev="PD" type="add">
        Add "sar:" URL protocol handling to policy section in environment.xml
        file.
    </action>
     <action dev="PD" type="add">
        Blocks no longre need to implement Block interface. Block interface
        is thus deprecated as is AbstractBlock. This was done to facilitate
        sharing of components between multiple containers.
    </action>

     <action dev="PD" type="add">
        Extrace Blocks to directory based on name deployed with rather than
        .sar name (to support multiple deployments of same .sar). Submitted
        By: Ulrich Mayring (ulim@denic.de)
    </action>
    <action dev="PD" type="add">
        Rework deployer such that jars are extracted to a temporary work
        directory and then deleted when application is undeployed. This is
        to work around the JVM locking and caching the jars and thus allowing
        users to redeploy applications. Submitted By: Ulrich Mayring
 (ulim@denic.de)
    </action>
    <action dev="PD" type="add">
        Updated build script so it will work when installed in a directory
        with spaces. Submitted By: dsmiley@mitre.org (David Smiley)
    </action>
    <action dev="PD" type="add">
        Use MX4J project to provide the JMX management kernel rather than
        RI.
    </action>
    <action dev="PD" type="add">
        Make phoenix use a temporary located in its hierarchy by setting
        the JVM system property "java.io.tmp". By default this temporary
        location is $PHOENIX_HOME/temp
    </action>
    <action dev="PD" type="add">
        Rework Embeddor so that it instantiates kernel components from a
        by reading the contents of conf/kernel.xml file.
        Submitted By: Joerg Bauer (bauer@denic.de)
    </action>
    <action dev="PD" type="add">
        Add XDoclet tasks to generate the manifest and BlockInfo files
        based on javadoc tags inserted into Blocks java file. Originally
        Submitted By: vinay nair (vinayc77@yahoo.com)
    </action>
    <action dev="SM" type="add">
        Added javadoc to more classes and added in package.html files
        where appropriate.
    </action>
    <action dev="PH" type="add">
        Added ApplicationListener objects that implement all same
        funcitonality as BlockListener but also provide support
        for Application Starting/Stopping/Failure events and
        provide access to SarMetaData. Consequently deprecated
        BlockListener interface.
    </action>
    <action dev="PD" type="add">
Enhanced DefaultManager to support authenticated connecitons.
Submitted By: "Jorg Bauer/Denic" (bauer@denic.de)
    </action>
    <action dev="MT" type="change">
Add support for Parameterizable blocks. Submitted by:
Brian Olsen (brian@mmmanager.org)
    </action>
    <action dev="PD" type="add">
Allow Blocks to declare that they are able to be exported to a Management
subsystem (ie JMS) by making their blocks declare (Management-access-points/)
        in their BlockInfo. Blocks will be exported to JMX with names like
        "application=Foo,name=MrBlock,role=org.apache.MyManagementInterface"
    </action>
  <action dev="PD" type="change">
    Validate the assembly.xml file and any BlockInfo files if they
    declare the DTD correctly.
  </action>
  <action dev="PD" type="change">
    Add native daemon support by using the daemon created in the
    http://wrapper.sourceforge.net/ project. Submitted By:
    Leif Mortenson (leif@silveregg.co.jp)
  </action>
  <action dev="PD" type="fix">
    Fixed bug where application names were inapropriately prefixed
    to log categories. Submitted By Antal Attila (atech@nolimits.ro)
  </action>
  <action dev="PD" type="fix">
    Fixed bug where application names were inapropriately prefixed
    to log categories.
  </action>
  <action dev="PD" type="change">
    Allow jars contained within the .sar file to declare dependencies
    on libraries using the standard JDK1.2+ Extension mechanism. For
    more information about optional packages, see the document
    Optional Package Versioning in the documentation bundle for your
    Java2 Standard Edition package, in the file
    guide/extensions/versioning.html.
  </action>
</release>
<release version="4.0a3" date="November 13, 2001">
  <action dev="PD" type="change">
    Add documentation describing BlockListener.
  </action>
  <action dev="PD" type="change">
    Fixed bug that allowed binary distributions to be built without
    copying xerces.jar into correct place.
  </action>
</release>
<release version="4.0a2" date="November 12, 2001">
  <action dev="PD" type="change">
    Update Phoenix to use the new Avalon Framework Logger interface rather than
    directly using LogKits Logger class. This required a backwards incompatible
    change in BlockContext. The getLogger() methods now return the Logger interface
    rather than LogKits Logger class. If a Block implements Loggable then it will
    be passed LogKits Logger, this is required for backwards compatability. If the
    Block implements LogEnabled it will receive the new style Logger.
  </action>
  <action dev="MT" type="add">
    Add support for undeploying and unistalling applications. Add support for separating
    out install phase from deployment phase and persisting information about
    application installations.
  </action>
  <action dev="PD" type="change">
    Rework the application deployment format (ie .sar format) to be more in line
    with other specifications. See docs/creating-a-server-application.html in distribution
    for current format description. The old format is deprecated but will still work.
  </action>
  <action dev="PH" type="add">
    Created the start of a Phoenix Developers Kit (PDK) that will enable
    developers to rapidly become accustom to developing Phoenix applications.
  </action>
  <action dev="PD" type="add">
    Started to incorporate the JMX code more fully into Phoenix kernel. Started
    doing this by refactoring the base MBeans and testing using the RIs agent.
  </action>
  <action dev="PD" type="change">
    Separated code that validated assembly of application into separate
    classes. The validation is now much stricter and requires that
    Blocks conform to established patterns. The validation phase should give
    more reasonable explanations for violations. Extra validation checks
    include verifying that services offered by a Block are actually interfaces,
    that there is no circular dependencies, that declared Blocks and BlockListeners
    actually implement Block or BlockListener interface, that the names of Blocks
    are valid etc.
  </action>
</release>
<release version="4.0a1" date="September 25, 2001">
  <action dev="BL" type="change">
    Too many things to enumerate here.  This is the first public release,
    and the code is still considered alpha.  In future releases, we will
    be much more careful to record the changes to Phoenix.
  </action>
</release>
<release version="3.1a2" date="Unreleased">
    <action dev="BL" type="add">
      Added stylesheet to convert Stylebook markup to DocBook markup.
    </action>
    <action dev="BL" type="change">
      Changed the documentation build process to use Cocoon to build
      the site.
    </action>
  <action dev="PD" type="remove">
    Legacy support for nested configuration elements in assembly file
    removed.
  </action>
  <action dev="PD" type="update">
    Simplified Loader and made it set ContextClassLoader before executing
    Main method. It will also use the System property phoenix.home if set
    rather than always trying to dynamically determine home directory.
  </action>
  <action dev="PD" type="add">
    Added SingleAppEmbeddor to launch a kernel to load a single Application.
    Patch supplied by "Eung-ju Park" (colus@isoft.co.kr). This is useful if
    you need to reuse the blocks in other contexts (such as in a Servlet).
  </action>
  <action dev="PD" type="add">
    Made default SystemManager a NoopSystemManager. Patch supplied
    by "Eung-ju Park" (colus@isoft.co.kr). To re-enable RMI manager a new
    command line switch "--remote-manager" was added.
  </action>
  <action dev="PD" type="update">
    Reworked SecurityManager setup. Instead of starting a security
    Manager inside the code it has been re-architectured so that the
    SecurityManager is set on the command line. This was to avoid a number
    of issues related to creating a URLClassLoader in an unprotected context
    before setting SecurityManager. ie As AccessControllerContext was null it
    is impossible to use ClassLoader.getResource(AsStream)(). This means that
    defining phoenix.insecure will no longer disable the SecurityManager. The
    replacement method is to set the native OS environment variable
    'PHOENIX_SECURE=false'.
  </action>
  <action dev="PD" type="update">
    Separate Parsing of CLI arguements into separate class (CLISetup).
    This is to facilitate launching Phoenix as a native daemon using
    Tomcats Services API.
  </action>
  <action dev="PD" type="add">
    Started Localizing text strings throughout Phoenix. This is done using
    ResourceManager and Resources from Avalon/Excalibur project.
  </action>
</release>
      </changes>
    </status>
