<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section>
  <title>Installation</title>

  <section>
    <title>Prerequisites</title>

    <para>MerlinStudio is developed on an NT/2000/XP basis. Also MerlinStudio
    should run on all other operating systems on which the Eclipse environment
    is available it is not tested yet.</para>

    <para>If anybody is testing MerlinStudio on other platforms, please let us
    know whether you succeeded.</para>

    <para>MerlinStudio is only running on eclipse 3.x and is not backward
    compatible to any previous version of eclipse.</para>

    <para>MerlinStudio is only running on JDK1.4 or higher. </para>

    <para>Tests with IBM JDKs are on the way.</para>

    <para><abbrev>Note:</abbrev> Either if you start MerlinStudio the first
    time or you create your first Merlin container project you have to be
    connected to the Internet! This is because of a repository service of
    Merlin which automatically reloads all needed resources from a central
    repository over the internet. </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Update manger</title>

    <para>Eclipse has got a very comfortable update manager through which you
    can install new software very easily.</para>

    <para>An other advantage of the Update Manger is that you can check if
    there are new or updated software modules of your loaded plugins
    available. You can than download and install those modules with the Update
    Manager without downloading the whole Plugin again.</para>

    <para>1. Please open the "Install/Update" Manager...</para>

    <para><inlinegraphic fileref="../../../resources/update1.gif" /></para>

    <para>2. and select "Search for new features to install".</para>

    <para><inlinegraphic fileref="../../../resources/update2.jpg" /></para>

    <para>3. Please press "next".</para>

    <para>You will enter the wizard page, which shows all currently available
    Update Sites. If you open the Update Manger the first time this page will
    empty.</para>

    <para>4. Now press the "Add Update Site..." button... </para>

    <para><inlinegraphic fileref="../../../resources/update3.gif" /></para>

    <para>and enter the name and the url of MerlinDevelopers Update Site as
    shown above. After pressing Ok, you should see something like
    this...</para>

    <para><inlinegraphic fileref="../../../resources/update4.gif" /></para>

    <para>If you open the Node in the TreeView, the Update Manager will
    connect to the Update Site. The "Next" button will be enabled if the
    connection is established. 5. Pressing the "Next" button will switch to
    the next Wizard Page and show all available versions of MerlinStudio.
    </para>

    <para><inlinegraphic fileref="../../../resources/update5.jpg" /> </para>

    <para>6. Select the feature and the version you want to install</para>

    <para>Pressing "Next" will lead you through the installation
    process.</para>

    <para>After finishing the installation process you will be asked to
    restart your Eclipse installation </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Zip file installation</title>

    <para>You can download the binary installation of MerlinStudio <link
    linkend="???">here</link>.</para>

    <para>To install MerlinStudio through the downloadable .zip file, please
    proceed with the following steps:</para>

    <para>1. Please make sure that you have installed a valid eclipse version.
    (see System Requirements).</para>

    <para>2. Extract the content of the .zip archive
    'MerlinStudio_[version].zip' into directory $ECLIPSE_HOME$/plugins, where
    $ECLIPSE_HOME$ is the directory where Eclipse is installed on your
    machine.</para>

    <para>3. Start Eclipse - if Eclipse is already running, please restart
    Eclipse.</para>

    <para>4. After you have restarted Eclipse you can check that
    MerlinDeveloper was successfully installed and loaded.</para>

    <para>First open the "About Dialog".</para>

    <para><inlinegraphic fileref="../../../resources/about_menu.jpg" />
    </para>

    <para>Please press Plug-in Details button in About dialog</para>

    <para><inlinegraphic
    fileref="../../../resources/AboutDialog.gif" /></para>

    <para>Now you should see this list:</para>

    <para><inlinegraphic
    fileref="../../../resources/Plug-in-list.gif" /></para>

    <para>If you don’t see those MerlinStudio Plug-ins in the list:</para>

    <para>Check that you have installed the correct version of MerlinStudio
    for the version of Eclipse that you are using.</para>

    <para>Check for error messages in file:
    $ECLIPSE_HOME$\workspace\.metadata\.log </para>

    <para>Shutdown Eclipse, delete this file, start Eclipse again, and try to
    use MerlinStudio. This process will remove old error messages and only
    include messages about the MerlinStudio or Eclipse loading process in the
    file listed above..</para>

    <para></para>
  </section>
</section>