<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.1//EN" "document-v11.dtd">
<document>
    <header>
        <title>Applications</title>

        <authors>
            <person name="Paul Hammant" email="Paul_Hammant@yahoo.com"/>
        </authors>
    </header>
    <body>

        <section>
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>
                This page lists applications that run on top of the Phoenix application kernel.
                Each of these applications applications are at different stages of development
                and evolution. Some of the "applications" are thin wrappers around existing
                products that make them capable of being managed from within Phoenix. While
                others are applications are assembled from reusable Blocks.
            </p>
            <p>
                The applications that take the wrapper approach are building on the sucess of
                pre-existing projects on the Web.  These could be at Apache or from
                SourceForge, and are not forked efforts.  They all do varioations of the same
                thing - namely instantiate the pre-existing project's main bean and expose it
                via a service interface to other phoenix blocks.  Some like HypersonicSQL
                present no methods in their service interface, their who interface to the world
                is through it's socket listener and a JDBC library on the client side.  All of
                the wrapped products are still launchable via their normal 'main' method in
                standalone mode.  These can be said to be dual mode, even if the code for
                phoenix compatability is in our CVS rather than their depot.
            </p>

        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Application list</title>

            <p>
                <strong>James</strong>:
                <link href="http://james.apache.org">http://james.apache.org</link>
            </p>
            <p>James is an email and news server.</p>

            <p>
                <strong>Ldapd</strong>:
                <link href="http://ldapd.sourceforge.net/">http://ldapd.sourceforge.net/</link>
            </p>
            <p>
                LDAPd is a pure Java LDAP v3 protocol, RFC 2251 compliant server. It's architecture
                is based on Matt Welsh's Staged Event Driven Architecture (SEDA).
            </p>

            <p>
                <strong>Telnetd</strong>:
                <link href="http://telnetd.sourceforge.net/">http://telnetd.sourceforge.net/</link>
            </p>
            <p>
                Ancient and insecure (over TCP/IP) protocol for having shell access to a computer.
            </p>

            <p>
                <strong>FTPServer</strong>:
                <link href="http://incubator.apache.org/projects/ftpserver">http://incubator.apache.org/projects/ftpserver</link>
            </p>
            <p>
                FTPServer is a solid FTPServer built on top of Phoenix.
            </p>

            <p>
                <strong>Jo! Web Server</strong>:
                <link href="http://www.tagtraum.com/jo.html">http://www.tagtraum.com/jo.html</link>
            </p>
            <p>
                Hendrik Schreiber has an excellent web server that is servlet capable.  It comes
                with a block for use within Phoenix. As a demo, it is possible to build a SAR
                file to see the default webapp of Jo! running under Phoenix control.  Jo! is Open-Source
                (LGPL license).
            </p>

            <p>
                <strong>OpenIM</strong>:
                <link href="http://www.javajabber.net/">http://www.javajabber.net/</link>
            </p>
            <p>
                Alexis Agahi and Vinaysahil Chandran have migrated OpenIM (formerly JabaServer) to 
                be Phoenix dependant. JabberServer is under a BSD-style license.
            </p>

            <p>
                <strong>Enterprise Object Broker (EOB)</strong>:
                <link href="http://www.enterpriseobjectbroker.org">http://www.enterpriseobjectbroker.org</link>
            </p>
            <p>
                This is an application server that uses the Jo! block.  It is not J2EE compatible.
            </p>

            <p>
                <strong>Jesktop</strong>:
                <link href="http://www.jesktop.com">http://www.jesktop.com</link>
            </p>
            <p>
                This is a desktop GUI that sits on Phoenix.
            </p>

            <p>
                <strong>PhoenixJMS</strong>:
                <link href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/phoenixjms">http://sourceforge.net/projects/phoenixjms</link>
            </p>
            <p>
                A JMS implementation hosted at SourceForge.
            </p>

            <p>
                <strong>Hypersonic SQL</strong>:
                <link href="http://sf.net/prohjects/hsqldb">http://sf.net/prohjects/hsqldb</link>
            </p>
            <p>
                A wrapper that allows Hsqldb (project
                <a href="http://sf.net/prohjects/hsqldb">http://sf.net/prohjects/hsqldb</a>)
                to be served from inside Phoenix.
            </p>

            <p>
                <strong>DeeBee</strong>:
                <link href="http://spice.sf.net">http://spice.sf.net</link>
            </p>
            <p>
                Also under infrequent development, an ambitious JDBC compliant RDBMS.
            </p>

        </section>

    </body>
</document>
