<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!-- 
 Copyright 2004 Apache Software Foundation
 Licensed  under the  Apache License,  Version 2.0  (the "License");
 you may not use  this file  except in  compliance with the License.
 You may obtain a copy of the License at 
 
   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 
 Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
 distributed  under the  License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
 WITHOUT  WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS  OF ANY KIND, either  express  or
 implied.
 
 See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
 limitations under the License.
-->

<document>

  <header>
    <title>Kernel Logging System</title>
    <authors>
      <person name="Stephen McConnell" email="mcconnell@apache.org"/>
    </authors>
  </header>

  <body>
    <section name="Logging Directive">

      <subsection name="Attributes">

        <table>
          <tr><th>Attribute</th><th>Required</th><th>Description</th></tr>
          <tr>
            <td>priority</td><td>no</td>
            <td>The default logging priority level. Allowable values include 
            INFO, WARN, ERROR, and DEBUG.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>target</td><td>no</td>
            <td>The name of the default logging target.</td>
          </tr>
        </table>

      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Nested Elements">

        <table>
          <tr><th>Element</th><th>Cardinality</th><th>Description</th></tr>
          <tr>
            <td><a href="target.html">target</a></td><td>n</td>
            <td>Logging target declartation.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><a href="category.html">category</a></td><td>n</td>
            <td>Internal kernel logging category directive.</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="Description">

<p>Logging services build above the Avalon framework abstract logging infrastructure.  Merlin provides the mechanisms through which logging hierarchies can be created, logging priorities assigned, and definition of log event output targets.  Logging directives may be includes at the kernel, container and component levels.</p>

<p>A kernel may be configured with an optional logging system creation directive.  The logging element declares the application wide default logging priority. A target element enables definition of a logging file to which log entries will be directed.  The target name attribute is the name referenced by category elements defined within the loggers element. Child category declarations must include a name (the logging category), and may optionally include a target and a priority attribute. The target defaults of "default" which corresponds to a internal default logging target that issue messages to System.out (unless overridden by a target named default). If the target is declared inside a category element, it must refer to a named target element.  The priority attribute may container one of the values <code>DEBUG</code>, <code>INFO</code>, <code>WARN</code> or <code>ERROR</code>.  The target must contain a single file element with the attribute <code>location</code> the corresponds to the name of the logging file.</p>

      </subsection>

      <subsection name="Sample XML">
<source><![CDATA[
    <logging priority="INFO" target="kernel">
      <target name="kernel">
        <file location="kernel.log" />;
      </target>
    </logging>
]]></source>

      </subsection>
    </section>
  </body>

</document>


