<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE document SYSTEM "dtd/document-v10.dtd">

<document>
  <header>
    <title>Excalibur - Overview</title>
    <authors>
      <person name="Avalon Documentation Team" email="avalon-dev@jakarta.apache.org"/>
    </authors>
  </header>
  <body>
    <s1 title="Refactoring!!">  
      <warn>
        There is a general reorganization of JAR files for Excalibur going 
        on at the moment (early April 2002).  This will be complete in a 
        couple of weeks.  For now, all the old docs have been migrated
        to new locations in the website, and will be joined by new pages
        shortly.  This is just a preview of the pages, and much will 
        change day by day.
      </warn>
    </s1>  
    <s1 title="Introduction">
      <p>
        Avalon Excalibur was created in order to ease development of
        new projects.  To that end, Excalibur contains a number of
        ready to use components and utilities that handle everything
        from command line parsing to thread concurrency management.
      </p>
      <p>
        The components in the Excalibur package have been well tested
        and do work reliably.  There is an associated project called
        "Scratchpad" that is a staging area for new Components.  When
        they have been sufficiently tested, we will include them in
        Excalibur.
      </p>
      <warn>
        The scratchpad code is provided for your benefit so that we
        can get feedback on whether the package is needed or wanted,
        and we can get error reports on it.  The components in
        Scratchpad are of varying quality or stability, depending on
        where they are in the development cycle.  They are <strong>NOT</strong>
        meant for production use.  You have been warned.
      </warn>
    </s1>
    <s1 title="Excalibur Sub-Projects">
      <s2 title="AltRMI - Alternative to RMI">
        <p>
          This is simpler, though controversial, alternative to RMI.  
        </p>
      </s2>
    </s1>
  </body>
  <footer>
    <legal>
      Copyright (c) @year@ The Jakarta Apache Project All rights reserved.
      $Revision: 1.4 $ $Date: 2002/04/13 10:55:40 $
    </legal>
  </footer>
</document>
