<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="dev@avalon.apache.org">Avalon Documentation Team</author>
    <title>Apache Avalon: Framework</title>
  </properties> 

  <body>
    <section name="Products">
      <subsection name="Component Model">

      <p>The Avalon Component model is made up of a combination of classic
      interfaces that define the artifacts exchanged between a container and 
      a component.  The requirements presented by a component to container
      are expressed using meta-info descriptors that are colocated with 
      component classes.  Interfaces and default implementations are described
      under Avalon Framework package. The meta-info descriptors and related tools
      are included under the Avalon Meta package.</p>

      <table>
        <tr><th>Product</th><th>Description</th></tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <p>
              <a name="framework"/>
              <a href="http://avalon.apache.org/framework/" name="framework">Avalon Framework API and Implementation</a>
            </p>
          </td>
          <td>
            <p>The Avalon Framework API and Implementation consists of interfaces that define relationships between commonly used application components, best-of-practice pattern enforcements, and several lightweight convenience implementations of the generic components.</p>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <p>
              <a name="meta"/>
              <a href="http://avalon.apache.org/meta/" name="meta">Avalon Meta</a>
            </p>
          </td>
          <td>
            <p>The Avalon Meta Model defines the functional criteria for component types and services. A Type definition contains information about deployment and runtime dependencies together with information about the services that a component type can provide.</p>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <p>
              <a name="util"/>
              <a href="http://avalon.apache.org/util/" name="util">Avalon Utilities</a>
            </p>
          </td>
          <td>
            <p>A set of utilities shared by framework components supporting default property
            management, environment variable resolution, exceptio reporting and a 
            parameterized map implementation (using within the repositroy package).</p>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <p>
              <a name="repository"/>
              <a href="http://avalon.apache.org/repository/" 
                  name="repository">Avalon Repository</a>
            </p>
          </td>
          <td>
            <p>A joint initative by the Avalon Project and the Apache Directory Project 
             in the development of an inteligent bootstrappig, resource replication,
             and artifact management framework.</p>
          </td>
        </tr>

      </table>
      </subsection>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
