<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="dev@avalon.apache.org">Avalon Documentation Team</author>
    <title>Why Avalon</title>
  </properties> 

  <body>
    <section name="Avalon Explained">
     <p>
      Avalon is a framework for component and container applications
      built on key design patterns such as Inversion of Control and
      Separation of Concerns and is available for the Java platform.  You
      can use Avalon to build any number of other applications from
      desktop centric Swing apps to complicated servers.  The Avalon
      framework is often used as the "underpinning" of a larger
      application or platform.  Such Avalon based
      applications include Apache Cocoon, Apache James, the Apache
      Directory Project, OpenIM and the Keel Framework.
     </p>
     <subsection name="What Avalon Isn't">
      <p>
       Avalon is not part of the J2EE stack.  While Avalon can be used
       in developing J2EE applications and even used to build a J2EE
       server, the Avalon platform is not part of J2EE or
       a J2EE application server.  Avalon is much simpler and does not
       include these advanced features out of the box.  That said, you
       might write a J2EE application which embeds Avalon (such as in
       a servlet) or you may embed a J2EE server in a larger
       Avalon-based container.
      </p>      
     </subsection>
     <subsection name="What Avalon Is">
      <p>
       The Avalon platform provides the following:
      </p>
      <ul>
       <li>A core framework for component programming</li>
       <li>A container system known as Merlin</li>
       <li>A set of container extensions called Facilities</li>
       <li>A component library</li>
      </ul>
      <p>
       When working with Avalon you may use one or all of these.  For
       more information on makeup of Avalon, see our <a
       href="overview.html">overview</a> page.
      </p>
     </subsection>
     <subsection name="Who Uses Avalon?">
      <p>
       Avalon users generally find themselves in one or more of the
       following roles:
      </p>
      <ul>
       <li>Avalon User: You are using another application which uses
      Avalon "under the hood."  Perhaps you are extending this
      application or are simply a user who wants to better understand
      the inner workings.
       </li>
       <li>Component Author: You are developing a component to be run
      in an Avalon container.  You may be assembling a set of
      components into a larger application block and then deploying
      that block and the Avalon container as a final complete
      application.</li>
      <li>Container Developer: You are extending an existing Avalon
      container or developing a new Avalon compliant container.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>
       Regardless of your role, there are certain technologies and
       concepts which are essentially prerequisites to Avalon
       development and use.  If you are not familar with these terms,
       please read the corresponding documentation:
      </p>
      <ul>
       <li>Java Platform</li>
       <li>Inversion of Control</li>
       <li>Separation of Concerns</li>
       <li>Component Oriented Programming</li>
      </ul>
     </subsection>
     <!--
     <subsection name="Why Use Avalon?">
     <p>
      To understand why someone would use Avalon, let's look at some
      of the problems Avalon solves.
     </p>
     <p>
     </p>
     </subsection>
     -->
     </section>
  </body>
</document>