<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.1//EN" "document-v11.dtd">

<document>
  <header>
    <title>Excalibur Compatibility - Overview</title>
    <authors>
      <person name="Berin Loritsch" email="bloritsch@apache.org"/>
    </authors>
  </header>
  <body>
    <section><title>Introduction</title>
      <p>
        Avalon is minimizing the number of projects and utilities it maintains
    because we need to focus on our charter.  However, we do have users
    who have used some of the projects that were previously released.  We
    can't just ignore their needs.  The compatibility project is the
    graveyard for projects we are no longer supporting.  It exists simply
    to let our users (and in some cases, our users' users) continue to
    use their legacy components until they migrate to better supported
    libraries.
      </p>
      <p>
        Most of the packages in this project have replacement libraries, but
    it is inevitable that some in here may not have a replacement yet--
    but the package falls outside our charter.  If you would like to
    volunteer to maintain those packages in your own library, please
    contact the <link href="mailto:dev@avalon.apache.org">Avalon
        Developer's List</link> and let them know of your availability.
        Packages with a definite and released replacement will be completely
    deprecated and point to the new classes in the new library.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section><title>Contents</title>
      <p>
        Currently the Compatibility has the packages in the following list.
    If the package has a replacement, then the replacement will be listed
    as well:
     </p>
     <ul>
       <li>org.apache.avalon.excalibur.cli --&gt; <link href="http://jakarta.apache.org/commons/cli/index.html">Jakarta Commons CLI</link></li>
       <li>org.apache.avalon.excalibur.collections --&gt; <link href="http://jakarta.apache.org/commons/collections/index.html">Jakarta Commons Collections</link></li>
       <li>org.apache.avalon.excalibur.concurrent --&gt; <link href="http://gee.cs.oswego.edu/dl/classes/EDU/oswego/cs/dl/util/concurrent/intro.html">Doug Lea's Concurrent Utilities</link></li>
       <li>org.apache.avalon.excalibur.io --&gt; <link href="http://cvs.apache.org/viewcvs/jakarta-commons-sandbox/io/">Jakarta Commons IO</link> (not released yet)</li>
     </ul>
    </section>
  </body>
  <footer>
    <legal>
      Copyright (c) @year@ The Jakarta Apache Project All rights reserved.
      $Revision: 1.3 $ $Date: 2003/07/07 16:52:43 $
    </legal>
  </footer>
</document>
