<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="dev@avalon.apache.org">Avalon Documentation Team</author>
    <title>Apache Avalon: Process</title>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="The Avalon Community">
     <p>
      Welcome to the Avalon community!
     </p>
     <p>
      Avalon, like all other projects at Apache, is a
      <em>meritocracy</em> and follows the <em>Apache Way</em> of
      community and project management.  The following documents
      help define these terms and form the guidelines by which Avalon operates.
     </p>
     <ul>
       <li><a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/decisions.html">
         Meritocracy</a></li>
       <li><a
         href="http://nagoya.apache.org/wiki/apachewiki.cgi?ApacheWay">
	 The Apache Way</a></li>
       <li><a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/roles.html">Roles
         and Responsibilities</a></li>
       <li><a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/guidelines.html">
         Jakarta Project Guidelines</a></li>
       <li><a href="http://incubator.apache.org/index.html">
         The Apache Incubator Project</a></li>
       <li><a href="http://apache.org/foundation/">The Apache Software
         Foundation</a> (ASF)</li>
       <li><a
     href="http://www.apache.org/licenses/cla.pdf">
         Contributor license Agreement</a> [PDF]</li>
       <li><a href="http://james.apache.org/contribute.html">Getting Involved</a></li>
     </ul>
    </section>
    <section name="Opening up Avalon's Repositories">
      <p>
        Avalon continually looks at ways to cooperate better with
        other projects, especially here at Apache. Recently, the
        Avalon team decided to open up the "avalon-excalibur"
        repository to the Apache Cocoon community. The response has
        been favorable as the libraries there now have a wider group
        of supporting developers. As a result, the Avalon team decided
        to take this process one step further and open up the
        "avalon-components" repository to both the Apache Cocoon and
        Apache JAMES projects.
      </p>
      <p>
       If you are from another Apache project, and would like all the
       committers from your project to have access to the Avalon
       Repositories, all you need to do is ask the Avalon PMC
       (pmc@avalon.apache.org). The repositories that are available
       for wider access are:
       </p>
       <ul>
        <li>avalon-components</li>
        <li>avalon-excalibur</li>
        <li>avalon-sandbox</li>
       </ul>
       <p>
         The PMC will let you know if your request is accepted or
         not. If you are interested in commit privileges, but are not
         part of one of the Apache projects, then you have to do it
         the old fashioned way and participate on the mailing lists
         and post patches, etc. We are taking advantage of the Apache
         infrastructure to make this happen.
       </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
