<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.1//EN" "document-v11.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>Guide - Creating a Block</title>
      
  <authors><person name="Phoenix Documentation Team" email="avalon-phoenix-dev@jakarta.apache.org"/></authors></header>
  <body>
    <section><title>Introduction</title>
      <p>
        This document will describe the process for creating your first block. There
        are essentially three steps that must be completed before your block is ready
        for assembling.
      </p>
      <ol>
        <li>Write the Block component.</li>
        <li>Write the BlockInfo meta-info description file.</li>
        <li>Package the component and related resources into a block jar file.</li>
      </ol>
    </section>
    <section><title>Writing the Block component</title>
      <p>
        Writing the Block is the main task you will be called to do. It follows all
        the rules of writing a standard Avalon component. If a block implements the
        Contextualizable interface it will be passed an instance of
        <code>org.apache.avalon.phoenix.BlockContext</code> which is an extended version
        of <code>org.apache.avalon.Context</code>. Other than this minor change the
        Block's container (the Phoenix Kernel) supports all the Avalon lifecycle
        methods or will in the near future (at the moment suspend/resume is not yet
        supported).
      </p>
      <p>
        The block can implement an interface if it wishes to export a service to external blocks. It is
        also possible to aquire services from other blocks in the <code>service()</code> method.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section><title>Write the BlockInfo</title>
      <p>
        You must create this file to indicate which services this Block depends upon
        and those services which it offers. It is more fully documented in the
        <link href="blockinfo-specification.html">BlockInfo Specification</link> document.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section><title>Create the jar package</title>
      <p>
        The final step is packaging up the implementation files, BlockInfos and other
        resources into a jar file.
      </p>
    </section>
     <section><title>Guide Contents</title>
       <ol>
        <li><link href="what-is-a-block.html">What is a block?</link></li>
        <li><link href="what-is-a-block-listener.html">What is a block listener?</link></li>
        <li><link href="what-is-an-application-listener.html">What is an application listener?</link></li>
        <li>How do I create a block?</li>
        <li><link href="making-phoenix-compatible-comps.html">How do I make my components phoenix-compatible?</link></li>
        <li><link href="blockinfo-specification.html">BlockInfo specification</link></li>
       </ol>
      </section>
  </body>
</document>
