<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <author email="dev@avalon.apache.org">Avalon Documentation Team</author>
    <title>Avalon Central</title>
  </properties> 

  <body>
    <section name="Magic's Project Model">

      <p>
      The notion of a POM (Project Object Model) is familiar to 
      Maven users.  Magic extends this concepts through complete support
      for transitive inheritance of dependency information together with
      build, test and runtime scopes.
      </p>

      <p>
      The magic system defintion is based on one or more index.xml files.
      The index.xml file contains resource, project, and plugin defintions.  
      </p>

      <p>
      A resource can be viewed as a logical artifact accessible from 
      a repository cache using group, name and version information. 
      Resources are resolved to file paths using the following convention:
      </p>

<source><![CDATA[
 [cache]/[group]/[type]s/[name]-[version].[type]
]]></source>

      <p><i>Example resource descriptor:</i></p>

<source><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<system>

  <resource>
    <info>
      <group>log4j</group>
      <name>log4j</name>
      <version>1.2.8</version>
      <type>jar</type>
    </info>
  </resource>

  ....

</system>
]]></source>

      <p>  
      A project extends the concept of a resource to include a local basedir 
      reference (the root of the project sources) and a set of dependencies.
      </p>

      <p><i>
      Example of two project defintions:
      </i></p>
<source><![CDATA[
  <project basedir="../../runtime/util/env">
    <info>
      <group>avalon/util</group>
      <name>avalon-util-env</name>
      <version>1.1.1</version>
    </info>
  </project>

  <project basedir="../../runtime/util/defaults">
    <info>
      <group>avalon/util</group>
      <name>avalon-util-defaults</name>
      <version>1.2.1</version>
    </info>
    <dependencies>
      <include key="avalon-util-env"/>
    </dependencies>
  </project>
]]></source>

      <p>
      In the above example Magic locates the project sources using the 
      declared basedir.  The name element is used as the default key 
      that is used when referencing the project - as is the case in the 
      second project defintions dependency declaration.
      </p>

      <p>
      Dependendency declarations within a project refernence the name of another 
      another project within the scope of an index.xml file or imported file.  As such, a 
      dependency declaration can be resolved to an artifact group, name, version
      and type, and from this information, a repository based resource can be 
      resolved, or in the case of a project or plugin reference, a target can be 
      built as part of a higher-level build scenario. 
      </p>

      <p>
      The declaration of dependendency implicitly introduced a dependency 
      by the dependee on the dependent of the dependency. In other words, dependency
      declarations are transative.  Magic provides support for the qualification of 
      transativate dependency inheritance relative to the following three policies: 
      </p>

      <ul>
        <li>BUILD</li>
        <li>TEST</li>
        <li>RUNTIME</li>
      </ul>

      <p><i>Example of scoped dependency.</i></p>

<source><![CDATA[
  <project basedir="../../runtime/meta/api">
    <info>
      <group>avalon/meta</group>
      <name>avalon-meta-api</name>
      <version>1.4.0</version>
    </info>
    <dependencies>
      <include key="avalon-framework-api"/>
      <include key="avalon-framework-impl" build="false" test="true" runtime="false"/>
    </dependencies>
  </project>
]]></source>

      <p>
      In the above example the avalon-framework-impl artifact will be included
      in path constructs for unit testing, but will be including in compile 
      classpaths or classpaths dealing with runtime information.
      </p>

      <p>
      A set of ant tasks use magic dependency information to construct respective  
      classpaths and classloaders when executing classic ant tasks such as 
      javac, junit, or custom tasks dealing with runtime artifacts (e.g. dynamic plugin
      loading, plugin data generators, deployment meta-data, etc., etc. )
      </p>

      <p>
      In the case of RUNTIME dependencies, Magic differntiates between the following
      classloader categories.
      </p>

      <ul>
        <li>API</li>
        <li>SPI</li>
        <li>IMPL</li>
      </ul>

      <p>
      A dependency declared as RUNTIME enabled with a tag API
      will result in the aggreggation of all of the dependents of the dependant within
      an API path scope.  The same principal holds true for SPI and IMPL tags with 
      the exception of non-repition of path entires in lower-level path declarations.
      In the impication of the term "lower-level" is realtive to the ordering of classloaders
      resolved from API, SPI and IMPL path declarations.  An IMPL classloader has a SPI
      classloader as parent, and in turn an SPI classloader has an API as parent. This
      chaining of classloaders provides the posibility for embedded applications to 
      control which classloader is supplied to their runtime sub-systems.  For example, 
      a plugin executing withing a particular environment can cotrol which classloader is 
      used (typically an API or SPI loader) when deployed child units (plugins, components, 
      etc.).
      </p>

      <p><i>Example of tagged dependencies.</i></p>

<source><![CDATA[
  <project basedir="../../runtime/merlin/impl">
    <info>
      <group>avalon/merlin</group>
      <name>avalon-merlin-impl</name>
      <version>3.3.0</version>
    </info>
    <dependencies>
      <include key="avalon-framework-api" tag="api"/>
      <include key="avalon-util-lifecycle" tag="api"/>
      <include key="avalon-util-extension-api" tag="spi"/>
      <include key="avalon-merlin-api" tag="spi"/>
      <include key="avalon-repository-api" tag="spi"/>
      <include key="avalon-meta-spi" tag="spi"/>
      <include key="avalon-repository-spi" tag="spi"/>
      <include key="avalon-logging-spi" tag="spi"/>
      <include key="avalon-composition-spi" tag="spi"/>
      <include key="avalon-composition-impl" tag="impl"/>
      <include key="avalon-util-configuration" tag="impl"/>
      <include key="avalon-repository-main" runtime="false"/>
      <include key="avalon-activation-impl" 
         build="false" test="false" runtime="false"/>
    </dependencies>
  </project>
]]></source>

      <p>
      The above classloader chaining strategy delivers
      the potential for applications to take control over the management of resourse 
      isolation - a fundamental security principal in component-based-development.
      Secondly, the actual implementation of classloader chaining becomes 
      strait-forward once a declarative model is put in place (in fact the 
      classloader creation can be totally automated as in the case with the 
      magic plugin task and several Avalon repository-enabled systems).
      </p> 

    </section>

  </body>

</document>

