<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE document SYSTEM "dtd/document-v10.dtd">

<document>
  <header>
    <title>Avalon Framework - Containers</title>
    <authors>
      <person id="PH" name="Paul Hammant" email="Paul_Hammant@yahoo.com"/>
    </authors>
  </header>
  <body>
    <s1 title="Introduction">
      <p> 
        There are various container that are aware of the Avalon-Framework interfaces.  
        They either support all or some of the interfaces.  They either add 
        <link href="guide-patterns-ioc.html">Inversion-of-Control</link> type interfaces 
        of their own constituting a specialized API, or do not, making them general 
        containers.
      </p>      
    </s1>      
    <s1 title="General Containers">
      <p>
        These typically run from the command line and are launched via a legacy main() method.
      </p>
      <s2 title="Avalon Phoenix">
        <p>
          This is a sister project to Avalon Framework.  It provides an environment 
          for launching of more or less unrestricted server applications as hosted 
          components.  These comps will be things like web-server, rdbms, EJB-server.
          See <link href="@PHOENIX_BASE@/index.html">Phoenix</link>.
        </p>
      </s2>
    </s1>
    <s1 title="Specialized Containers">
      <p>
        These typically run inside something else and are launched by that something else.
      </p>
      <s2 title="Excalibur Component Manager">
        <p>
          This is used by various applications like Cocoon. Cocoon is run inside the 
          Sun specified servlet context of a web-app.  It is designed for such 
          Servlet-context reuse.  See TODO.
        </p>
      </s2>
      <s2 title="Enterprise Object Broker (EOB)">
        <p>
          The reference implementation of the EJB-replacement container runs on top of 
          Phoenix.  EOB supports a subset of the Avalon Framework interfaces but allows
          RPC publishing of arbitary interfaces apparent in a hosted components object
          model.  See <link href="http://eob.sourceforge.net/">EOB</link>.
        </p>
      </s2>      
    </s1>    
  </body>
  <footer>
    <legal>
      Copyright (c) @year@ The Jakarta Apache Project All rights reserved.
      $Revision: 1.1 $ $Date: 2002/06/09 19:34:59 $
    </legal>
  </footer>
</document>
