<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="dev@avalon.apache.org">Avalon Documentation Team</author>
    <title>Apache Avalon: Containers</title>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="Products">
      <subsection name="Container Solutions">

      <p>Within Avalon their are a number of container solutions. This 
      reflects a historical divergence and a present convergence within 
      the area of containment technology within Avalon. The original 
      containment solutions ECM and Phoenix focussed on very different 
      approaches to component management.  The ECM model dealt with 
      primarily pooled objects used in environments such as 
      <a href="http://cocoon.apache.org/">Cocoon</a>. The
      Phoenix model dealt with a strict singleton model supporting 
      project such as <a href="http://james.apache.org">James</a>.  
      Recent developments have resulted in the 
      release of 
      <a href="http://avalon.apache.org/excalibur/fortress/">Fortress</a> 
      and <a href="http://avalon.apache.org/merlin/">Merlin</a>.  
      Fortress replaces the ECM solution
      and is positioned as a migration vehicle for components to move
      towards Avalon's latest container - Merlin.  The Merlin container
      is an attempt at being a flexible and adaptive embedded container
      that leverages a set of common containment facilities.
      Merlin provides support for legacy Phoenix components and includes 
      many of of the lifestyle concepts introduced within Fortress.</p>

      <table>
        <tr><th>Product</th><th>Description</th></tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <p>
              <a name="merlin"/>
              <a href="http://avalon.apache.org/merlin/index.html">Avalon Merlin</a>
            </p>
          </td>
          <td>
            <p>
                The Merlin project deals with the broad area of service
                and component management. The Merlin system is a container
                that provides comprehensive support for the management of
                complex component-based systems. Merlin uses a component
                meta-model to facilitate the automated assembly and
                deployment of simple and composite components.
            </p>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <p>
              <a name="fortress"/>
              <a href="http://avalon.apache.org/excalibur/fortress/">Avalon Fortress</a>
            </p>
          </td>
          <td>
            <p>
              Fortress contains a framework to help you create your own
              avalon containers.  It boasts asynchronous management of your
              component instances, high scalability, easier maintenance of
              your code, and easy embedding into various environments like
              servlet engines.
            </p>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <p>
              <a name="ecm"/>
              <a href="http://avalon.apache.org/excalibur/component.html">ECM</a>
            </p>
          </td>
          <td>
            <p>
            This package contains the ExcaliburComponentManager (ECM). ECM has 
            been depricated in favour of the new Fortress container.</p>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <p>
              <a name="phoenix"/>
              <a href="http://avalon.apache.org/phoenix/index.html">Phoenix</a>
            </p>
          </td>
          <td>
            <p>
              Phoenix is a micro-kernel designed and implemented on top of 
              the Avalon framework. It provides a number of facilities to 
              manage the environment of Server Applications. Such facilities 
              include log management, classloading, thread management and 
              security.
            </p>
          </td>
        </tr>
      </table>
      </subsection>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
 