<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>
    <header>
        <title>Excalibur Instrument - Instruments</title>
        <authors>
            <person name="Leif Mortenson" email="leif@apache.org"/>
        </authors>
    </header>
    <body>
        <s1 title="Instruments">
            <p>
                Instruments are the actual hooks used by a component to make profiling or
                instrumentation information available to the outside world.  Instruments are
                created by a component during their initialization phase and then referenced
                throughout the life of the component.  The Instruments should be created whether
                the component is registered with an InstrumentManager or not.  This removes the
                necessity for the component to do anything special if not registered.
            </p>
            <p>
                The Instruments themselves are designed to be extremely lightweight.  In cases
                where an InstrumentManager is not present, or where it is present but output is
                not currently being collected, the Instrument effectively becomes a noop.
            </p>
            <p>	
                There are currently two types of Instruments available for use by components.
                So far they have proven to be enough to profile any type of quantitative
                information.
            </p>
            <p>
                The first is the CounterInstrument.  Counters are used to, well, count the number
                of times that something happens.  They can be used to keep track of the number of
                times a method is called, a resource is accessed, etc.   The CounterInstrument
                provides two methods.  The first, increment(), which ups the counter by 1.  And
                the second, instrument( count ), which accepts any positive integer.  The later
                method can be used in cases where increment would normally have to be called a
                large number of times.   For example, the number of iterations in a sort algorithm.
            </p>
            <p>
                The second type of Instrument is the ValueInstrument.  ValueInstruments are used
                to track quantities over time.  Examples are the size of a pool, the current
                memory usage of the JVM, etc.   ValueInstruments provide a single method,
                setValue( value ).
            </p>
        </s1>
    </body>
</document>
