<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>
    <header>
        <title>Excalibur Instrument - Instrumentables</title>
        <authors>
            <person name="Leif Mortenson" email="leif@apache.org"/>
        </authors>
    </header>
    <body>
        <s1 title="Instrumentables">
            <p>
                The Instrumentable interface is required to be able to register a component with
                an InstrumentManager.  The interface makes it possible for the InstrumentManager
                to query the component about what Instruments and child Instrumentables is making
                available.
            </p>
            <p>
                The interface provides four methods.  The first two, setInstrumentableName and
                getInstrumentableName are used to get and set the name of the Instrumentable.
                This name is similar to a category name in logger frameworks.  The name is
                required by the InstrumentManager to be able to provide clients with a way to
                request and access instrumentation output.  The name should not include any
                periods as they are used as separators in a hierarchy of Instrumentables and
                their Instruments.  The name of top level Instrumentable is usually set by the
                object which creates the component.  Usually this is a container.  If the
                creating object is not aware of the Instrument API then it is possible that
                setInstrumentableName will never be called.  Components should be able to
                function properly under this condition.   In the case of child Instrumentables,
                it is the responsibility of the parent to call setInstrumentableName.
            </p>
            <p>
                The third and fourth methods, getInstruments and getChildInstrumentables, are
                each called once by an InstrumentManager to query the Instrumentable for a list
                of the Instruments and child Instrumentables that is making available.
            </p>
            <p>
                Please see the <link href="instrumentable-howto.html">Instrumentable How-To</link>
                for an example.
            </p>
            <p>
                Implementing the Instrumentable interface directly requires a little bit of work,
                but is necessary in cases where the parent class can not be controlled.  In most
                situations, it is possible to extend one of the two helper classes provided with
                the API, AbstractInstrumentable and AbstractLogEnabledInstrumentable.   Either
                of these classes provide methods to add Instruments and Child Instrumentables to
                the lists to be published.  All of the above methods are handled behind the scenes.
                The second helper class is available for classes also wish to extend the
                AbstractLogEnabled class provided with Framework.  (If this class is used, then
                Instrument requires that the avalon-framework.jar file be included in the
                classpath.)
            </p>
            <p>
                Please see the
                <link href="abstract-instrumentable-howto.html">AbstractInstrumentable How-To</link>
                for an example.  An example of the AbstractLogEnabledInstrumentable helper class is
                not included as its usage is identical to AbstractInstrumentable.
            </p>
        </s1>
    </body>
</document>
