<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>
    <header>
        <title>Excalibur Instrument - Overview</title>
        <authors>
            <person name="Leif Mortenson" email="leif@apache.org"/>
        </authors>
    </header>
    <body>
        <s1 title="Why Instrument Was Created">
            <p>
                Instrument was created out of a desire to provide a standard API for adding
                profiling or instrumentation hooks into an application or class.  As any
                application grows in complexity the ability to understand the interactions
                and resource usages of its individual components becomes increasingly difficult.
            </p>
            <p>
                Logging tools have helped by making it possible to maintain debug and informational
                log messages throughout the code.  This output can be enabled or disabled at will
                and then used to help understand the flow of an application.
            </p>
            <p>
                However, while logging is indispensable in many areas, it is not very useful at
                tracking quantitative information over time.  There was a need to be able to
                collect information over time to be able to monitor quantities like memory usage,
                pool sizes, counts, and durations over time.
            </p>
        </s1>
        <s1 title="When To Use Instrument">
            <p>
                Instrument is an API for enabling the collection of qualitative information from a
                component.  The API itself has no dependencies on the Avalon framework and can thus
                be used to instrument any application.
            </p>
            <p>
                Instrumenting an application should be thought of in the same way as adding support
                for logging.   Just like logging, instrumentation can be very useful in all phases
                of an applications life.  During development, information collected can be
                invaluable to help track down bottlenecks, leaks, or simply in understanding the
                flow of a system.  Once an application has been released, the instrument output
                can be used to monitor the resources consumed by the application as well as the
                loads that are placed on it over time.
            </p>
        </s1>
        <s1 title="Portability">
            <p>
                The Instrument API has been carefully designed in such a way as to remove any
                limitations on where components making use of the API can be used.  Most logger
                APIs require that a logger be configured before components making use of their
                APIs will function correctly.  Failing to configure the component with a logger
                will using result in NullPointerExceptions or similar problems.  
            </p>
            <p>
                Instrumentation takes a different approach by providing an opaque API which makes
                it possible for a component providing instrumentation output to function the same
                whether the output is being collected or not.  Output is provided to the outside
                world by making use of Instrument instances within the component.  The component
                will work identically even if run in an environment which is completely unaware
                of the Instrument API.  This should remove all portability fears.
            </p>
        </s1>
        <s1 title="Performance">
            <p>
                Another concern with any tool like this is performance.  Many users ask, "How will
                instrumenting my component affect its performance."  The answer is that the
                Instrument API was designed from the beginning with performance in mind.  When a
                component implementing the Instrumentable interface is instantiated, it must be
                registered with an InstrumentManager.  Upon registration, the component is queried
                for a list of any Instruments or child Instrumentables that it would like to
                publish.   If the component is never registered, or until the time that the
                registered Instument output is actually needed, the Instruments them selves are
                effectively noops in the code.  For this reason, other than in the case of an
                extremely tight loop, instruments can be added to code without any fear of a
                negative impact on their performance.
            </p>
            <p>
                When an InstrumentManager receives a request for output from a particular
                Instrument, there will be a slight performance hit caused by the actual collection
                of the output.  However, the collection of data points has been designed to avoid
                affecting performance as much as possible.
            </p>
        </s1>
        <s1 title="Core Concepts">
            <p>
                When working with the Instrument API, there are two main classes that you need to
                be aware of.
            </p>
            <p>
                The first is the Instrumentable interface.  This interface must be implemented by
                any class wishing to be registered with an InstrumentManager and then publish
                Instrument output.  The interface provides methods used by an InstrumentManager
                to query the component for its name, Instruments, as well as any child
                Instrumentable objects.  See the
                <link href="instrumentables.html">Instrumentables</link> section for more
                information.
            </p>
            <p>
                The second is the Instrument interface.  It should not be necessary to implement
                this interface yourself.  The Instrument API provides to two implementations which
                have so far covered all requred types of output.  The first is the
                CounterInstrument which is used to count the number of times an event takes place.
                The second is the ValueInstrument which is useful for tracking changes in a value
                over time.  Examples of the later are memory allocation, pool sizes and durations.
                See the <link href="instruments.html">Instruments</link> section for more
                information.
            </p>
            <p>
                The Instrument API also provides InstrumentManager and InstrumentManageable
                interfaces.   The InstrumentManager interface must be implemented by any class
                which wishes to act as an InstrumentManager.  In most cases the
                DefaultInstrumentManager can be used.  It is provided by the
                <link href="../instrument-manager/">Instrument Manager</link> project.
            </p>
            <p>
                The InstrumentManageable interface should be implemented by any component which
                needs to be able to have access to the InstrumentManager.  In most cases, only
                elements of a container need to implement this interface.
            </p>
            <p>
                In order to make use of the Instrumentation added to components, they must be
                registered with an Instrument Manager.  If an Instrument Manager aware container
                is used, this will be automatic.  Currently, both the
                <link href="../component/">Excalibur Component Manager</link> and
                <link href="../fortress/">Excalibur Fortress</link> know how to manage and register
                Instrumentable components.
            </p>
            <p>
                Once an application is running with an active, users can connect to the
                InstrumentManager and request instrumentation output from any registered
                Instrument in the application.  The most common method of connecting to an
                InstrumentManager is to make use of the
                <link href="../instrument-client/">Instrument Client</link>.  The Instrument
                Client provides a Swing based GUI that makes it easy to monitor several Instruments
                at once.   For other options read over the documentation of the
                <link href="../instrument-manager/">Instrument Manager</link>.
            </p>
        </s1>
    </body>
</document>
