<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>
  <header>
    <title>Avalon Excalibur's Tweety - FAQ</title>
    <authors>
      <person name="Leo Simons" email="leosimons@apache.org"/>
    </authors>
  </header>
  <body>
	<s1 title="Why tweety?">
		<p>Some people found avalon very complex to get started with. We decided a good way to
		fix this was to provide an implementation specifically geared at learning how avalon
		works: tweety.</p>
	</s1>
	<s1 title="Why name an avalon container 'tweety'???">
		<p>"No clues in this fishy. No clues in that fishy."<br /><br />
		One popular avalon subproject (also a container) is called Phoenix. It has quite a
		lot of features (runs multiple applications, classloader management, isolation,
		automagically provides management for hosted applications, etc etc etc). It is also
		quite difficult to get started with at first.<br />
		"Phoenix" (among other things) is the name of a powerful mythological bird. Tweety
		is the name of a sweet yellow canary. Some of us geeks think it is funny.</p>
	</s1>
	<s1 title="Will you add feature XXX to tweety?">
		<p>"Gimme a 'P', gimme a 'U', gimme a 'D', 'D', 'Y'."<br /><br />
		Very unlikely. That would probably increase tweety in size and complexity, which we
		don't want.</p>
	</s1>
	<s1 title="My question is not answered. What do I do?">
		<p>"Oh goody, goody. A surprise for me."<br /><br />
		Start by reading the documentation provided. If your question is not answered
		there, post a detailed message to the
		<link href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/mail2.html#Avalon">Avalon User list</link>.
		We will try to help you out.</p>
	</s1>
	<s1 title="I followed the instructions in the getting started document, but Tweety doesn't work. What do I do?">
		<p>"Aaaah. The poor puddy tat fall down."<br /><br />
		That's not supposed to happen! Please contact us through the user mailing list
		(see above) with detailed information of your system configuration and what steps
		you took that led to an error message, and of course the error message.</p>
	</s1>
	<s1 title="So what's this 'Egg' thing?">
		<p>"Ooh! A wittle playmate. I never see you before... "<br /><br />
		It is what you get when you remove everything but the lifecycle handling from
		Tweety; this is how Tweety started. It has hatched and grown since though. We
		kept the Egg lying around because the code is a little easier to follow if you
		want to understand what the lifecycle is from looking at code.</p>
	</s1>
	<s1 title="Knock it off with the stupid quotes already!!!">
		<p>"I did! I did taw a puddy tat!"<br /><br />
		You can find a lot more, along with pictures, icons, sounds, animations, what
		have ye, just by typing "tweety" into the google search box. Just in case you
		came here looking for just that,
		<link href="http://www.scally.com/lorrie/tweety.html">this site</link>
		will get you started.
		In case you really can't stand it, go and read our serious documentation about
		multi-dimensional separation of concerns 'n stuff!</p>
	</s1>
  </body>
  <footer>
    <legal>
      Copyright (c) @year@ The Jakarta Apache Project All rights reserved.
      $Revision: 1.4 $ $Date: 2002/07/14 10:40:49 $
    </legal>
  </footer>
</document>
