<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>
  <header>
    <title>Avalon Excalibur's Tweety - Overview</title>
    <authors>
      <person name="Leo Simons" email="leosimons@apache.org"/>
    </authors>
  </header>
  <body>
	<s1 title="Introduction">
		<p>Tweety is a minimalist container explicitly designed for educational purposes, and
		educational purposes only.</p>

		<p>In other words, if you want to learn the concepts behind avalon,	and see some examples
		of how to apply them, tweety is your starting point. If you need to actually write really
		cool components for a production environment, look elsewhere.</p>

		<p>Tweety is currently in an alpha stage (though it works just fine!). You can only get
		it from CVS at this point. Expect downloadables in two weeks or so.</p>

		<note>We can use a lot of help with tweety, especially in the form of simple tweetified
		components and documentation patches. Chirp!</note>
		
		<note>Some of these pages describe non-existent documentation, examples, or features.
		We'll get to it!</note>
	</s1>

	<s1 title="Hello World in 2 minutes">
		<p>Following the instructions on the <link href="install.html">Install</link> and
		<link href="getting-started.html">Getting Started</link> pages should get you a working
		Hello World demo in no time at all. If you haven't got Apache Ant installed yet, it'll take a
		bit longer (around 15 minutes, I guess).</p>
	</s1>
	<s1 title="The available documentation">
		<s2 title="The Tweety FAQ">
			<p>Tweety has a very modest FAQ (Frequently Asked Questions document). If your
			question is not answered there or in the documentation, post a detailed message to the
			<link href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/mail2.html#Avalon">Avalon User list</link>.</p>
		</s2>
		<s2 title="JavaDocs">
			<p>All of the Tweety code has complete javadocs. If you're an experienced java
			programmer, you can probably figure out everything that happens when you invoke tweety
			just by looking at the code.</p>

			<p><link href="api/">API Documentation</link></p>
		</s2>

		<s2 title="Avalon for beginners">
			<p>This is a hands-on, example-based tutorial for people that are new to avalon. It
			will eventually migrate to the main avalon site. It introduces avalon framework and its
			concepts, using Tweety for the example code.</p>

			<p><link href="avalon-for-beginners.html">Start the tutorial</link></p>
		</s2>

		<s2 title="The Avalon Container HOWTO">
			<p>This is a tutorial for the advanced avalon user who wants to write his own container.
			It is assumed you are familiar with all the avalon framework definitions, interfaces,
			and contracts.</p>

			<p><link href="avalon-container-howto.html">Start the tutorial</link></p>
		</s2>
	</s1>
  </body>
  <footer>
    <legal>
      Copyright (c) @year@ The Jakarta Apache Project All rights reserved.
      $Revision: 1.3 $ $Date: 2002/07/02 16:30:17 $
    </legal>
  </footer>
</document>
