<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="dev@avalon.apache.org">Avalon Documentation Team</author>
    <title>Apache Avalon: Containers</title>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="Container Overview" >
      <subsection name="Purpose" >
        <p>
          The purpose of the container is to manage the components under its
          care. That typically involves various creation and destruction
          stages, or what we call the LifeCycle. Part of the creation stages
          is the different needs the component has, such as it may need a 
          Logger, so the container has to provide it, it may need some type
          of configuration and the container has to provide, and so on.
        </p>
        <p>
          The container is also responsible to fulfill other concerns of the
          management contract, such as LifeStyle, Security, Dependencies, 
          JAR handling and so on. Basically, the container should take care
          of everything required to get the component operational.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection name="Container-Component Contract" >
        <p>
          Avalon Framework and associated material specifies, among other
          things a contract between the component and the container. That 
          means that if the component fulfills its obligations, the container
          will provide the component with its needs. Example; If the component
          declares that it implements LogEnabled, the container will provide
          the component with an initialized and ready-to-use Logger instance.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      
    </section>
    
    <section name="Container Provisions" >
      <subsection name="Logging" >
        <p>
          If the component declares that it implements the LogEnabled inteface,
          a ready-to-use, Logger instance will be provided through the method;
        </p>
<source>
    public void enableLogging( Logger logger )
    {
    }
</source>
        <p>
          The Merlin container supports both LogKit and Log4J logging subsystem,
          and please look at the 
          <a href="../../../../products/runtime/system/logging/index.html">Avalon Logging</a> subsystem for 
          details.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection name="Dependencies" >
        <p>
          There are many ways on how to resolve dependencies between components.
          Avalon uses a method called <em>Lookup Injection</em>, which means 
          that the container will hand over a ServiceManager to the component,
          if the component implements the Serviceable interface.
        </p>
<source>
    public void service( ServiceManager manager )
    {
    }
</source>
        <p>
          The ServiceManager will only provide the component with components
          that satisfy the <strong>dependencies</strong> declaration in the
          component's 
          <a href="../../../../products/runtime/system/meta/meta/info/type/index.html">Type descriptor</a> 
          (.xinfo). If it attempts to lookup anything outside the declared
          dependencies, the container is expected to throw a ServiceException.
        </p>
        <p>
          And Merlin is so clever that the component will never be deployed
          if the dependencies could not be satisfied, so if the component
          follows its obligations, i.e. only looking up declared dependencies,
          the container will supply the solution, always!
        </p>
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection name="Configuration" >
        <p>
          Many components are generic and can be tweaked into doing slightly
          different things, according to some settings. We call those settings
          Configuration, and is supply to the component if the component
          implements the Configurable interface.
        </p>
<source>
    public void configure( Configuration conf )
    {
    }
</source>
        <p>
          The above construct allow for very complex Configurations, using
          XML nested elements, but not any XML, it must follow certain rules.
          See <a href="/api/org/apache/avalon/framework/configuration/Configuration.html">
          Configuration</a> API docs for details.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection name="Contextualization" >
        <p>
          Contextualization is about establishing a containment context. That
          means that there must be certain container features available to the
          component for it to function properly. This is slightly different
          from normal service dependencies, as context entries can be of any
          type, such as java.io.File for the standard "urn:avalon:home" 
          context entry.
        </p>
<source>
    public void contextualize( Context context )
    {
    }
</source>
        <p>
          It is also possible to create custom context entries. 
          <a href="../../../about/tutorials/advanced/context.html">Read more about it.</a>
        </p>
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection name="Repository" >
        <p>
          We have all been in <em>JAR Hell</em>, which means that it is hard
          to keep track of which Jars are required, and more importantly which
          version of each. And that is only for your build system. When you
          start deploying the applications, this grows into a nightmare.
          This has been highlighted for quite some time within
          The Apache Software Foundation, and Maven has addressed it for build
          systems, and recently (March 2004) a new more generic project called
          Depot started in the incubator, which will address this problem.
        </p>
        <p>
          Avalon has in the meantime created the 
          <a href="../../../../products/runtime/system/repository/index.html">Avalon Repository</a> which allows
          the applications to be distributed without any Jars, and the right
          versions of the Jars will be picked up at one or many central 
          repositories. This system is compatible with the Maven repositories,
          so we have instantly access to hundreds of projects at repositories,
          such as ibiblio.org.
        </p>
      </subsection>
    </section>
    
    <section name="Container Deployment Cases" >
      <subsection name="Stand-alone Server" >
        <p>
          The most straight forward deployment case is the stand-alone server,
          that is started from the command-line. No programming is required, 
          and there are heaps of command-line arguments available. Read about
          the details <a href="../../../../products/runtime/execmodes/cli.html">here</a>.
        </p>
        <p>
          Merlin even supports that it is bootstrapped, with a tiny JAR, which 
          will pick up and start Merlin (or any other compliant artifact) from a
          central repository. One can on the command-line specify which version
          of Merlin one wishes to start, and provide the application block 
          reference, effectively selecting which application to start.
        </p>
        <p>
          If a central repository is not desirable, Merlin's binary distribution
          contains all that is required to run, except the application block
          itself, which may either be local or online.
        </p>
      </subsection>
    
      <subsection name="Stand-alone GUI Application" >
        <p>
          There is actually no difference between a stand-alone server and a
          stand-alone GUI application. In fact, with good Component Oriented
          practices, one can completely separate the business logic in the
          application, and provide a GUI interface or a Web interface simply
          by changing the block definition file.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection name="Running as a Windows NT/XP Service" >
        <p>
          Merlin is capable of starting as a Windows NT/XP Service. You can
          read about how on <a href="../../../about/installation/nt.html">this 
          page.</a>
        </p>
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection name="Embedded in generic Application" >
        <p>
          If you have an existing application that you want to complement with
          Avalon component management, without refactoring the whole application
          into components, you will need to create Merlin embedded inside your
          application. About 10-15 lines of code is currently required, where
          the InitialContext is established, the Directives are setup and a 
          Kernel is created. It 
          <a href="../../../../products/runtime/execmodes/servlet.html">looks 
          more complicated</a> than it is, but it is
          extremely powerful, and allows the same features as the stand-alone
          server, in fact the small bootstrapper in the stand-alone case, does
          exactly the same thing. 
        </p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="Embedded in a Servlet" >
        <p>
          If the Servlet engine allows, it is possible to embedd Merlin inside
          a Servlet. The code required to do it, can be seen
          <a href="../../../../products/runtime/execmodes/servlet.html">here</a>.
          It is expected that this Servlet will undergo some enhancement prior
          to be officially released in the Merlin distribution. This is to
          ensure maximum usability for our users.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection name="Embedded in Application Server" >
        <p>
          Embedding in Application Servers can prove to be a lot more 
          complicated than in generic Application, since the App Servers very
          often imposes restrictions on the parts that it hosts, such as
          security restrictions, classloading restrictions and similar. It is
          basically a case of trying to get a operating system running inside
          another operating system, both competing for the same resources.
        </p>
        <p>
          One of the objectives of the Avalon community is to work out what is
          possible, and how, and what can not be done, in this area.
        </p>
      </subsection>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
