<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>
  <header>
    <title>Excalibur Event - Thread</title>
    <authors>
      <person name="Berin Loritsch" email="bloritsch@apache.org"/>
    </authors>
  </header>
  <body>
    <s1 title="Why Thread Was Created">
      <p>
        Thread is a temporary fork of the official Excalibur Thread package.
        The main difference is that we use MPool to back the Thread Pool.
        This portion will go away when we can have an official Excalibur
        Thread project without any dependencies on the Pool package.
      </p>
    </s1>
    <s1 title="When To Use Thread">
      <p>
        The short answer at this time is not to use this version of Thread
        for your own development.  It is a <em>temporary</em> fork to get
        the Command Manager in <link href="command.html">Command</link>
        working without an artificial dependency on a separate pooling
        package when we already have one.
      </p>
    </s1>
    <s1 title="Core Concepts">
      <p>
        Thread has two main peices that you use: Thread Pool and Thread
        Control.  The Thread Pool is what you use to execute some work.
        It pools a thread from a pool of threads, and returns a Thread
        Control.  The Thread Control will allow you to "control" the
        pooled thread.
      </p>
      <s2 title="Thread Pool">
        <p>
          The Thread Pool interface is how the Thread Manager in Command
          will execute the Commands.  Most implementations of the Thread
          Pool will block if there are no more threads available.  When
          one of the threads in use are finished, the pool will then execute
          the Command.
        </p>
      </s2>
      <s2 title="Thread Control">
        <p>
          The Thread Control allows you to perform normal Thread manipulations
          without the Thread Pool losing real control over its collection
          of Threads.  The commands that can be used are join(), interrupt(),
          isFinished(), and getThrowable().
        </p>
      </s2>
    </s1>
  </body>
  <footer>
    <legal>
      Copyright (c) @year@ The Jakarta Apache Project All rights reserved.
      $Revision: 1.1 $ $Date: 2002/09/26 00:46:04 $
    </legal>
  </footer>
</document>
