<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="dev@avalon.apache.org">Avalon Documentation Team</author>
    <title>Avalon Central</title>
  </properties> 
 <body>

   <section name="Issue Tracking">
    <p>
    Avalon uses the <a href="http://issues.apache.org/jira">ASF JIRA</a>
    issue tracker to manage feature requests
    and bug fixes.  Anyone can browse project reports,
    though you will need an account to submit new issues.  Please
    submit requests to the appropriate project module (when in doubt,
    send a message to the developers mailing list).
    </p>
    <table>

     <tr>
       <th>Project</th>
       <th>Description</th>
     </tr>

     <tr>
       <td><a href="http://issues.apache.org/jira/secure/BrowseProject.jspa?id=10530">Avalon Central</a></td>
       <td>Site docs, General Issues</td>
      </tr>

      <tr>  
       <td><a href="http://issues.apache.org/jira/secure/BrowseProject.jspa?id=10532">Avalon Planet</a></td>
       <td>Components and facilities.</td>
      </tr> 

      <tr>  
       <td><a href="http://issues.apache.org/jira/secure/BrowseProject.jspa?id=10533">Avalon Tools</a></td>
       <td>Avalon's build system and general developer tools.</td>
      </tr> 

      <tr>  
       <td><a href="http://issues.apache.org/jira/secure/BrowseProject.jspa?id=10425">Merlin Runtime</a></td>
       <td>Avalon Merlin RI Container.</td>
      </tr>

      <tr>  
       <td><a href="http://issues.apache.org/jira/secure/BrowseProject.jspa?id=10531">Merlin Studio</a></td>
       <td>Exclipse support tools for Merlin component development.</td>
      </tr>

    </table>
    <p>
     A full list of the projects can be found at <a href="http://issues.apache.org/jira">http://issues.apache.org/jira</a>
     in the Avalon, Avalon Merlin, and Avalon Components categories.
    </p>

     <subsection name="Submitting Patches">
	    <p>Generate patches using <code>cvs diff -u</code>, or <code>diff -u</code>.
	    Please create your patches relative to the root of the cvs module the patch
	    should be applied to. Please compile changes to multiple files
	    in a single patch file. Make sure the patch adheres to the coding standards,
	    and includes appropriate javadoc.</p>
	    
	    <p>When you've built the patch, file a new bug report in JIRA if one
	    does not exist yet, explain the reason behind the patch, how the patch fixes
	    the issues, and add the patch as an attachment.</p>
	    
	    <p>If your patch is not getting applied or there is no response, start nagging
	    the developers (politely, please :D) on the developers mailing list.</p>    
	    
	    <p>Please submit documentation patches against the XML sourcefiles used
	    for generating the documentation, and not against the documentation
	    itself.  Site documentation issues can be opened in the Avalon Framework's
          Documentation module.</p>

     </subsection>

   </section>
  </body>
</document>
